<!-- $Id: authentication_primer.xml,v 1.13 2003/04/15 16:31:54 guildenstern Exp $ -->
<chapter id="ch06">
   <chapterinfo>
     <authorgroup>
       <author>
           <firstname>Gene</firstname><surname>McKenna</surname>
       </author>
       <author>
           <firstname>Charles</firstname><surname>Miller</surname>
       </author>
     </authorgroup>
   </chapterinfo>
<title>Authentication</title>

<sect1>
	<title>What is Authentication?</title>

	<para>
	Authentication is the process of determining if a user or entity is who
	he/she claims to be. This can be done with different methods discussed 
	later on.
	</para>

	<para>
	In a web application it is easy to confuse authentication and session
	management (dealt with in a later section). Users are typically
	authenticated by a username and password or similar mechanism. When
	authenticated, a session token is usually placed into the user's browser
	(stored in a cookie or an URL). This allows the browser to send a token each
	time a request is being made, thus performing entity authentication on
	the browser. The act of user authentication usually takes place only
	once per session, but entity authentication takes place with every
	request.
	</para>

	<sect2>
		<title>Types of Authentication</title>

		<para>
		As mentioned there are principally two types of authentication
		and it is worth understanding the two types and determining
		which you really need to be doing.
		</para>

		<para>
		User Authentication is the process of determining that a user is
		who he/she claims to be.
		</para>

		<para>
		Entity authentication is the process of determining if an entity
		is who it claims to be.
		</para>

		<para>
		Imagine a scenario where an Internet bank authenticates a user
		initially (user authentication) and then manages sessions with
		session cookies (entity authentication).  If the user now
		wishes to transfer a large sum of money to another account 2
		hours after logging on, it may be reasonable to expect the
		system to re-authenticate the user!
		</para>
	</sect2>

	<sect2>
		<title>Browser Limitations</title>

		<para>
		When reading the following sections on the possible means of
		providing authentication mechanisms, it should be firmly in the
		mind of the reader that ALL data sent to clients over public
		links should be considered "tainted" and all input should be
		rigorously checked. SSL will not solve problems of
		authentication nor will it protect data once it has reached the
		client. Consider all input hostile until proven otherwise and
		code accordingly.
		</para>
	</sect2>

	<sect2>
		<title>HTTP Basic</title>

		<para>
		There are several ways to do user authentication over HTTP. The
		simplest is referred to as HTTP Basic authentication. When a
		request is made to a URI, the web server returns a HTTP 401
		unauthorized status code to the client:
		</para>

		<para>
		HTTP/1.1 401 Authorization Required
		</para>

		<para>
		This tells the client to supply a username and password.
		Included in the 401 status code is the authentication header.
		The client requests the username and password from the user,
		typically in a dialog box. The client browser concatenates the
		username and password using a ":" separator and base 64 encodes
		the string. A second request is then made for the same resource
		including the encoded username password string in the
		authorization headers.
		</para>

		<para>
		HTTP authentication has a problem in that there is no mechanism
		available to the server to cause the browser to 'logout'; that
		is, to discard its stored credentials for the user.  This
		presents a problem for any web application that may be used from
		a shared user agent.
		</para>

		<para>
		The username and password of course travel in effective
		clear-text in this process and the system designers need to
		provide transport security to protect it in transit. SSL or TLS
		are the most common ways of providing confidentiality and
		integrity in transit for web applications.
		</para>
	</sect2>

	<sect2>
		<title>HTTP Digest</title>

		<para>
		There are two forms of HTTP Digest authentication that were
		designed to prevent the problem of username and password being
		interceptable. The original digest specification was developed
		as an extension to HTTP 1.0, with an improved scheme defined for
		HTTP 1.1. Given that the original digest scheme can work over
		HTTP 1.0 and HTTP 1.1 we will describe both for completeness.
		The purpose of digest authentication schemes is to allow users
		to prove they know a password without disclosing the actual
		password. The Digest Authentication Mechanism was originally
		developed to provide a general use, simple implementation,
		authentication mechanism that could be used over unencrypted
		channels.
		</para>

		<mediaobject>
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata fileref="images/HTTP_digest.png" format="PNG"/>
			</imageobject>
			<textobject>
			<phrase>HTTP Digest Authentication</phrase>
			</textobject>
		</mediaobject>

		<para>
		As can be seen by the figure above, an important part of
		ensuring security is the addition of the data sent by the server
		when setting up digest authentication. If no unique data were
		supplied for request, an attacker would simply be able to replay
		the digest or hash.
		</para>

		<para>
		The authentication process begins with a 401 Unauthorized
		response as with basic authentication. An additional header
		WWW-Authenticate header is added that explicitly requests digest
		authentication. A nonce is generated (the data) and the digest
		computed.  The actual calculation is as follows:
		</para>

		<orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
			<listitem>
				<para>String "A1" consists of username, realm,
				password concatenated with colons.</para>
				<para>owasp:users@owasp.org:password</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>Calculate MD5 hash of this string and
				represent the 128 bit output in hex</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>String "A2" consists of method and
				URI</para>
				<para>GET:/guide/index.shtml</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>Calculate MD5 of "A2" and represent output
				in ASCII.</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>Concatenate A1 with nonce and A2 using
				colons</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>Compute MD5 of this string and represent
				it in ASCII</para>
			</listitem>
		</orderedlist>

		<para>
		This is the final digest value sent.
		</para>

		<para>
		As mentioned HTTP 1.1 specified an improved digest scheme that
		has additional protection for
		</para>

		<itemizedlist mark="opencircle" spacing="compact">
			<listitem>
				<para>Replay attacks</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>Mutual authentication</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>Integrity protection</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para>The digest scheme in HTTP 1.0 is susceptible to replay
		attacks. This occurs because an attacker can replay the
		correctly calculated digest for the same resource. In effect the
		attacker sends the same request to the server. The improved
		digest scheme of HTTP 1.1 includes a NC parameter or a nonce
		count into the authorization header. This eight digit number
		represented in hex increments each time the client makes a
		request with the same nonce. The server must check to ensure the
		nc is greater than the last nc value it received and thus not
		honor replayed requests.
		</para>

		<para>Other significant improvements of the HTTP 1.1 scheme are
		mutual authentication, enabling clients to also authenticate
		servers as well as allowing servers to authenticate clients and
		integrity protection.
		</para>
	</sect2>

	<sect2>
		<title>Forms Based Authentication</title>

		<para>
		Rather than relying on authentication at the protocol level,
		web based applications can use code embedded in the web
		pages themselves. Specifically, developers have previously used
		HTML FORMs to request the authentication credentials (this is
		supported by the TYPE=PASSWORD input element).  This allows a
		designer to present the request for credentials (Username and
		Password) as a normal part of the application and with all the
		HTML capabilities for internationalization and accessibility.
		</para>

		<para>
		While dealt with in more detail in a later section it is
		essential that authentication forms are submitted using a POST
		request. GET requests show up in the user's browser history and
		therefore the username and password may be visible to other
		users of the same browser.
		</para>

		<para>
		Of course schemes using forms-based authentication need to
		implement their own protection against the classic protocol
		attacks described here and build suitable secure storage of
		the encrypted password repository.
		</para>

		<para>
		A common scheme with Web applications is to prefill form fields
		for users whenever possible. A user returning to an application
		may wish to confirm his profile information, for
		example. Most applications will prefill a form with the
		current information and then simply require the user to
		alter the data where it is inaccurate. Password fields,
		however, should never be prefilled for a user. The best
		approach is to have a blank password field asking the
		user to confirm his current password and then two
		password fields to enter and confirm a new password.
		Most often, the ability to change a password should be
		on a page separate from that for changing other profile
		information.
		</para>

		<para>
		This approach offers two advantages. Users may carelessly leave
		a prefilled form on their screen allowing someone with physical
		access to see the password by viewing the source of the page.
		Also, should the application allow (through some other security
		failure) another user to see a page with a prefilled password
		for an account other than his own, a "View Source" would again
		reveal the password in plain text. Security in depth
		means protecting a page as best you can, assuming other
		protections will fail.
		</para>

		<para>
		Note: Forms based authentication requires the system designers
		to create an authentication protocol taking into account the
		same problems that HTTP Digest authentication was created to
		deal with. Specifically, the designer should remember that forms
		submitted using GET or POST will send the username and password
		in effective clear-text, unless SSL is used.
		</para>
	</sect2>

	<sect2>
		<title>Digital Certificates (SSL and TLS)</title>

		<para>
		Both SSL and TLS can provide client, server and mutual entity
		authentication. Detailed descriptions of the mechanisms can be
		found in the SSL and TLS sections of this document.  Digital
		certificates are a mechanism to authenticate the providing
		system and also provide a mechanism for distributing public keys
		for use in cryptographic exchanges (including user
		authentication if necessary). Various certificate formats are
		in use.  By far the most widely accepted is the International
		Telecommunication Union's X509 v3 certificate (refer to RFC
		2459). Another common cryptographic messaging protocol is
		PGP. Although parts of the commercial PGP product (no longer
		available from Network Associates) are proprietary, the OpenPGP
		Alliance (http://www.openPGP.org) represents groups who
		implement the OpenPGP standard (refer to RFC 2440).
		</para>

		<para>
		The most common usage for digital certificates on web systems is
		for entity authentication when attempting to connect to a secure
		web site (SSL). Most web sites work purely on the
		premise of server side authentication even though client side
		authentication is available. This is due to the scarcity of
		client side certificates and in the current web deployment model
		this relies on users to obtain their own personal certificates
		from a trusted vendor; and this hasn't really happened on any
		kind of large scale.
		</para>

		<para>
		For high security systems, client side authentication is a must
		and as such a certificate issuance scheme (PKI) might need to be
		deployed. Further, if individual user level authentication is
		required, then 2-factor authentication will be necessary.
		</para>

		<para>
		There is a range of issues concerned with the use of digital
		certificates that should be addressed:
		</para>

		<itemizedlist mark="opencircle" spacing="compact">
			<listitem>
				<para>
				Where is the root of trust? That is,
				at some point the digital certificate must
				be signed; who is trusted to sign the
				certificate?  Commercial organizations provide
				such a service identifying degrees of rigor in
				identification of the providing parties,
				permissible trust and liability accepted by the
				third party. For many uses this may be
				acceptable, but for high-risk systems it may be
				necessary to define an in-house Public Key
				Infrastructure.
				</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>Certificate management:  who can generate
				the key pairs and send them to the signing
				authority?
				</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>
				What is the Naming convention for the
				distinguished name tied to the certificate?
				</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>
				What is the revocation/suspension process?
				</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>
				What is the key recovery infrastructure process?
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para>
		Many other issues in the use of certificates must be
		addressed, but the architecture of a PKI is beyond the scope of
		this document.
		</para>
	</sect2>

	<sect2>
		<title>Entity Authentication</title>

		<sect3>
			<title>Using Cookies</title>

			<para>
			Cookies are often used to authenticate the user's
			browser as part of session management mechanisms. This
			is discussed in detail in the session management section
			of this document.
			</para>
		</sect3>

		<sect3>
			<title>A Note About the Referer</title>

			<para>
			The referer [sic] header is sent with a client
			request to show where the client obtained the URI. On
			the face of it, this may appear to be a convenient way
			to determine that a user has followed a path through an
			application or been referred from a trusted domain.
			However, the referer is implemented by the user's
			browser and is therefore chosen by the user. Referers
			can be changed at will and therefore should never be
			used for authentication purposes.
			</para>
			<para>
			Do not even rely on getting something in the referer field
			at all. There are clients and proxies out there which delete
			this field on default.
			</para>
		</sect3>
	</sect2>

	<sect2>
		<title>Infrastructure Authentication</title>

		<sect3>
			<title>DNS Names</title>
			<para>
			There are many times when applications need to
			authenticate other hosts or applications. IP addresses
			or DNS names may appear like a convenient way to do
			this. However the inherent insecurities of DNS mean
			that this should be used as a cursory check only, and as
			a last resort.
			</para>
		</sect3>

		<sect3>
			<title>IP Address Spoofing</title>
			<para>
			IP address spoofing is also possible in certain
			circumstances and the designer may wish to consider the
			appropriateness. In general use gethostbyaddr() as
			opposed to gethostbyname(). For stronger authentication
			you may consider using X.509 certificates or
			implementing SSL.
			</para>
		</sect3>
	</sect2>

	<sect2>
		<title>Password Based Authentication Systems</title>

		<para>
		Usernames and passwords are the most common form of
		authentication in use today. Despite the improved
		mechanisms over which authentication information can be carried
		(like HTTP Digest and client side certificates), most systems
		usually require a password as the token against which
		initial authorization is performed. Due to the conflicting goals
		that good password maintenance schemes must meet, passwords are
		often the weakest link in an authentication architecture. More
		often than not, this is due to human and policy factors and can
		be only partially addressed by technical remedies. Some best
		practices are outlined here, as well as risks and benefits for
		each countermeasure. As always, those
		implementing authentication systems should measure risks and
		benefits against an appropriate threat model and protection
		target.
		</para>

		<sect3>
			<title>Usernames</title>

			<para>
			While usernames have few requirements for security, a
			system implementor may wish to place some basic
			restriction on the username.  Usernames that are
			derivations of a real name or actual real names can
			clearly give personal detail clues to an attacker.
			Other usernames like social security numbers or tax
			ID's may have legal implications.  Email addresses are
			not good usernames for the reason stated in the
			Password Lockout section.
			</para>
		</sect3>

		<sect3>
			<title>Storing Usernames and Passwords</title>

			<para>
			In all password schemes the system must maintain
			storage of usernames and corresponding passwords to be
			used in the authentication process. This is still true
			for web applications that use the built in data store of
			operating systems like Windows NT. This store
			should be secure. By secure we mean the passwords should
			be stored in such a way that the application can compute
			and compare passwords presented to it as part of an
			authentication scheme, but the database should not be
			able to be used or read by administrative users or by
			an adversary who manages to compromise the system.
			Hashing the passwords with a simple hash algorithm like
			SHA-1 is a commonly used technique.
			</para>
		</sect3>

		<sect3>
			<title>Ensuring Password Quality</title>

			<para>
			Password quality refers to the entropy of a password and
			is clearly essential to ensure the security of the
			users' accounts. A password of "password" is obviously a
			bad thing. A good password is one that is impossible to
			guess.  That typically is a password of at least 8
			characters, one alphanumeric, one mixed case and at
			least one special character (not A-Z or 0-9). In web
			applications special care needs to be taken with
			meta-characters.
			</para>
		</sect3>

		<sect3>
			<title>Password Lockout</title>

			<para>
			If an attacker is able to guess passwords without the
			account becoming disabled, then eventually he will
			probably be able to guess at least one password.
			Automating password checking across the web is very
			simple!  Password lockout mechanisms should be employed
			that lock out an account if more than a preset number
			of unsuccessful login attempts are made.  A suitable
			number would be five.
			</para>

			<para>
			Password lockout mechanisms do have a drawback,
			however.  It is conceivable that an adversary can try
			a large number of random passwords on known account
			names, thus locking out entire systems of users.  Given
			that the intent of a password lockout system is to
			protect from brute-force attacks, a sensible strategy
			is to lockout accounts for a number of hours.  This
			significantly slows down attackers, while allowing the
			accounts to be open for legitimate users.
			</para>
		</sect3>

		<sect3>
			<title>Password Aging and Password History</title>

			<para>
			Rotating passwords is generally good practice. This
			gives valid passwords a limited life cycle.  Of course,
			if a compromised account is asked to refresh its
			password then there is no advantage.
			</para>
		</sect3>

		<sect3>
			<title>Automated Password Reset Systems</title>

			<para>
			Automated password reset systems are common. They allow
			users to reset their own passwords without the latency
			of calling a support organization. They clearly pose
			some security risks in that a password needs to be
			issued to a user who cannot authenticate himself.
			</para>

			<para>
			There are several strategies for doing this. One is to
			ask a set of questions during registration that can be
			asked of someone claiming to be a specific user. These
			questions should be free form, i.e., the application
			should allow the user to choose his own question and
			the corresponding answer rather than selecting from a
			set of predetermined questions.  This typically
			generates significantly more entropy.
			</para>

			<para>
			Care should be taken to never render the questions and
			answers in the same session for confirmation; i.e.,
			during registration either the question or answer
			may be echoed back to the client, but never both.
			</para>

			<para>
			If a system utilizes a registered email address to
			distribute new passwords, the password should be set to
			change the first time the new user logs on with the
			changed password.
			</para>

			<para>
			It is usually good practice to confirm all password
			management changes to the registered email address.
			While email is inherently insecure and this is certainly
			no guarantee of notification, it is significantly harder
			for an adversary to be able to intercept the email
			consistently.
			</para>
		</sect3>

		 <sect3>
			<title>Password Recovery</title>
			<para>
			Password recovery becomes necessary when the user of a system is no longer able to authenticate themselves because they have lost or forgotten their password. Any systems that require authentication will need to have some policy or procedure for password recovery.
			</para>
			
			<sect4>
			<title>General Advice</title>
			<para>Good Practices</para>
			<para> When recovering a password, always assign, or require the user to choose a new password. You shouldn't be storing unhashed passwords anywhere anyway. If the recovery procedure is compromised, the real user will be unable to log in. This makes it easier to detect fraud. (obviously) Log all recovery attempts Only allow recovery once within a particular time-period (three months) Subsequent recovery attempts will result in a direction to call customer service, where a rep will manually perform the recovery procedure. When the user calls, the rep can guarantee that the previous recovery attempt was genuine. It's an opportunity to educate the user.
			</para>

			<para>Things to Consider</para>
			<para>
			Is the process automated, or does it require human intervention? If the process requires human contact, are you ready to deal with users from other countries, or who do not speak the same language as you? To what degree can you inconvenience your users before they decide not to bother? Is it a problem if they do? What steps can you take to make sure the users don't forget their passwords in the first place?
			</para>
			</sect4>

       			<sect4>
			<title>Specific Techniques</title>
			
			<sect5>
			<title>In Person Identification</title>
			<para>
			Obviously, the best thing to do is to have the user physically present themselves to you with 100 points worth of photographic identification. This is a form of secondaryauthentication recovery, and is very secure. Like all optimal solutions, this is generally impossible in a web environment, and is a particular inconvenience to users. That said, if you need security, and you have the luxury of physical offices near the vast majority of your customers (I'm thinking of banks and government departments here), this is worth thinking about.
			</para>

			<para>Advantages</para>
			<para>
			Best, legally defensible security. In case of fraud, you might remember what they look like
			</para>

			<para>Disadvantages</para>
			<para>
			Requires human intervention in all cases. Requires the user to take time out (during business hours) to recover their password. May be difficult or impossible for the user dependent on their distance from your offices.
			</para>
			</sect5>

			<sect5>
			<title>Faxed Documentation</title>
			<para>
			 Another form of secondary authentication, the user does not present themselves, but transmits a facsimile of some kind of official identification such as a passport or drivers license. This is a quite common technique, but may not be as reliable as it seems.
			 </para>
			 <para>Good Practices</para>
			 <para>
			 Keep a copy of the identification on file from signup-time, to be compared in the event of recovery. ID documents look different from state to state and country to country. Unless you have some idea what it should look like, you can easily be fooled by a competent graphic artist.
			 </para>
			 <para>Advantages</para>
			 <para>
			 So long as the identification is on file, this is reasonably secure, as an attacker must be a competent forger, and know the correct serial numbers for the documents. If not, this is easily defeated by a committed attacker.
			 </para>
			 <para>Disadvantages</para>
			 <para>
			 If the identification papers are on file with you, they may be on file with many other companies. Similarly, if the user is willing to fax you their passport for identification purposes, they may be socially engineered into sending the same documentation to an attacker. Requires human intervention in all cases. User must have access to a fax machine. User must be willing to store their documentation with you (the user may quite justifiably fear identity theft if your records are compromised or misused) Digital forgery is possible, and is masked by the poor quality of fax transmissions. Identity documents are replaced or renewed, so some secure mechanism for replacing the filed ID is necessary. Does not cover how to get the new password to the user after they've identified themselves over the fax.
			 </para>
			</sect5>

			<sect5>
			<title>Simple Email recovery</title>
			<para>
			E-mailing the password to the user's registered address is the most common form of recovery on public websites. It is a weak form of "secure channel" recovery, where it is assumed the path between the server and the user's email client is secure. Of course, this assumption isn't particularly defensible, but the process requires almost no human intervention, and is "secure enough" for most applications.
			</para>
			<para>Good practices</para>
			<para>
			Send the user a one-time password, based on the user's password hash and a timestamp. That way, the recovery password can only be used until the main password is changed, and can be expired if not used for 24 hours.  The email does not become a security problem if it's archived.
			</para>
			<para>Advantages</para>
			<para>
			Highly automated Familiar, and very easy for the user to understand Attacks rely on compromising some part of the communications chain between server and user. Thus, targetting an attack against a particular individual requires some effort.
			</para>
			<para>Disadvantages</para>
			<para>
			Vulnerable at every point that the email could be intercepted. Users may not understand that by sharing their email account with family members, they are making passwords available and susceptible to opportunistic attacks.  Once an attacker has access to any mailserver, they can methodically break the accounts of all users of that server. If the mailserver or gateway from which the recovery mails originate is compromised, it's game over for everybody.
			</para>
			</sect5>

			<sect5>
			<title>Encrypted Email Recovery</title>
			<para>
			A secure channel method, sending an email encrypted with some secret only known to the customer is possible. The obvious method is to have the user provide some public key at registration time, and send their recovery emails encrypted with that key.
			</para>
			<para>Good Practices</para>
			<para>
			If you are going to provide this, it must be optional.  Most people do not have public keys. If encrypted email recovery is selected by the user, disable alternative methods of recovery All practices for good email recovery still apply here. Remember to provide mechanisms to cater for key expiration and revocation.
			</para>
			<para>Advantages</para>
			<para>
			Highly secure
			</para>
			<para>Disadvantages</para>
			<para>
			Not a good general solution, the PGP-using population of the world is infinitesimal. Key management remains one of those issues that always looks easy on paper, but tends to be much harder to implement.
			</para>
			</sect5>

			<sect5>
			<title>Question and Answer</title>
			<para>
			Another form of secondary authentication. When registering the account, the user records some personal information. To recover the password, the user must answer questions based on this personal information, either to a web page, or over the phone to a representative. The questions and answers become a shared secret, a form of secondary password. Remember how we warn people not to base their passwords on their names, pets names or dates of birth? The security of this technique varies based on the choice of questions: the ease of an attacker guessing the questions, and the ease of researching the answers. It's amazing how many institutions believe that your date of birth and your mother's maiden name are sufficiently obscure to protect your bank account. One implementation would be to request the information that was supplied during registration, such as address, phone number and credit-card details. This sort of information may, however, be quite easy for an attacker to come across or socially engineer. Properly managed, this technique is more secure than e-mailing the password in the case of generalised or opportunistic attacks. However, due to its susceptibility to research, it is less secure against targetted attacks.
			</para>
			<para>Good Practices</para>
			<para>
			Have a large pool of questions, of which the user only has to answer a subset during signup/recovery. The more questions in the pool, the more research an attacker must do. On the other hand, having a set of 50 personal questions in the sign-up process will scare people away. Some systems allow the user to choose the questions as well. This is a bad idea, as users don't understand security, and will either make things too easy for an attacker to guess, or too hard for themselves to work out what the hell they were thinking, six months hence. If the process is not automated, and for some insane reason you have the original password on file, "What did you think the password was?" can be an effective question.
			</para>
			<para>Advantages</para>
			<para>
			Less susceptible to opportunistic attacks than mailed passwords. Still able to be automated, or performed by untrained employees following scripts and exercising next to no personal judgement.
			</para>
			<para>Disadvantages</para>
			<para>
			It's hard to come up with a good set of questions. The better the attacker knows the target, the less secure it is. Unless the questions got very personal, my brother could probably answer 90% of them for me. Users may consider personal questions to be an intrusion. The answers may not be easy to match automatically, leading to false rejections.
			</para>
			</sect5>

			<sect5>
			<title>Callback</title>
			<para>
			Another secure channel method. The user makes a request for a new password, and the recovery secret is sent to a phone or pager number supplied by the user during registration. This method can be combined with "Question and Answer" for a pretty effective recovery system. It mostly limits attacks to friends and family (who have access to the telephone and the personal information), and since the time of the call is logged and the attacker has to talk to the representative, it's easier to trace fraud. Proprietary systems exist that automate this process, adding secondary authentication via voice recognition.
			</para>
			<para>Advantages</para>
			<para>
			When combined with Question and Answer, this is probably the most secure method after encrypted email.
			</para>
			<para>Disadvantages</para>
			<para>
			Company bears the cost of phone calls, which might be difficult if you have international users. Resource-intensive if done manually.
			</para>
			</sect5>		

			</sect4>

       	 </sect3>

		<sect3>
			<title>Sending Out Passwords</title>

			<para>
			 In highly secure systems passwords should only be sent
			 via a courier mechanism or reset with solid proof of
			 identity. Processes such as requiring valid government
			 ID to be presented to an account administrator are
			 common.
			</para>

			<para>
			In most systems sending the a temporary password to the user's email address on file is adequate. This password should be randomly generated and pre-expired. This temporary password allows the user to initially log in to a password-changing page. 
			</para>
		</sect3>

		<sect3>
			<title>Single Sign-On Across Multiple DNS Domains</title>

			<para>
			With outsourcing, hosting and ASP models becoming more
			prevalent, facilitating a single sign-on experience to
			users is becoming more desirable. The Microsoft Passport
			and Project Liberty schemes will be discussed in future
			revisions of this document.
			</para>

			<para>
			Many web applications have relied on SSL as providing
			sufficient authentication for two servers to communicate
			and exchange trusted user information to provide a
			single sign on experience. On the face of it this would
			appear sensible. SSL provides both authentication and
			protection of the data in transit.
			</para>

			<para>
			However, poorly implemented schemes are often
			susceptible to man in the middle attacks.  A common
			scenario is as follows:
			</para>

			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/mitm_attack.png" format="PNG"/>
				</imageobject>
				<textobject>
				<phrase>A Man-In-The-Middle Attack</phrase>
				</textobject>
			</mediaobject>

			<para>
			The common problem here is that the designers typically
			rely on the fact that SSL will protect the payload in
			transit and assumes that it will not be modified. He of
			course forgets about the malicious user. If the token
			consists of a simple username then the attacker can
			intercept the HTTP 302 redirect in a Man-in-the-Middle
			attack, modify the username and send the new request. To
			do secure single sign-on the token must be protected
			outside of SSL. This would typically be done by
			using symmetric algorithms and with a pre-exchanged key
			and including a time-stamp in the token to prevent
			replay attacks.
			</para>
		</sect3>

	</sect2>
</sect1>
</chapter>














