   <!-- $Id: ch02.xml,v 1.12 2003/01/28 20:01:43 heartogold Exp $ -->
<chapter label="2">
    <chapterinfo>
        <authorgroup>
            <author>
                <firstname>Mark</firstname>
                <surname>Curphey</surname>
            </author>
            <author>
                <firstname>Adrian</firstname>
                <surname>Wiesmann</surname>
             </author>
        </authorgroup>
    </chapterinfo>
    
<title>Overview</title>

<sect1>
	<title>
	What Are Web Applications? 
	</title>

	<para>
	In its most basic form a web application is a client/server software application
	that interacts with users or other systems using HTTP. For a user the
	client is most likely be a web browser like Microsoft Internet Explorer or
	Netscape Navigator; for another software application this would be
	an HTTP user agent that acts as a browser on behalf of the system. The end user
	views web pages and is able to interact by sending choices to and
	from the system. The functions performed can range from relatively
	simple tasks like reading content or searching a local directory for a file or reference,
	to highly sophisticated applications that perform real-time sales and
	inventory management across multiple business partners. The technology behind
	web applications has developed at the speed of light. Traditionally
	simple applications were built with a common gateway interface
	application (CGI) often written in C or Perl and typically running on the web server itself that
	maybe connected to a simple database (again often on the same host). Modern enterprise web applications 
        typically are written in Java (or similar languages) and run on distributed 
        application servers, connecting to multiple data sources through complex business 
        logic tiers. They can consist of hundreds of servers each performing specific tasks 
        or fucntions. Detailed discussion of web archictures can be found in Chapter 5 
        of this document.
	</para>

	<para>
	There is a lot of confusion about what a web application actually
	consists of and where the security problems lie. While it is true that the 
        problems so often discovered and reported are product specific, they are often 
        logic and design flaws in the application, and not necessarily flaws in 
        the underlying web products or technology.
	</para>

	<mediaobject>
		<imageobject>
			<imagedata fileref="images/layer_overview.jpg" format="JPEG"/>
		</imageobject>
		<textobject>
		<phrase>Web Application Tiers</phrase>
		</textobject>
	</mediaobject>

	<para>
	It can help to think of a web application as being made up of three
	logical tiers or functions.
	</para>

	<para>
	Presentation Tiers are responsible for presenting the data to the end
	user or system. The web server serves up data and the web browser
	renders it into a readable form, which the user can then interpret. It
	also allows the user to interact by sending back parameters, which the
	web server can pass along to the application. This "Presentation Tier"
	includes web servers like Apache and Internet Information Server and web
	browsers like Internet Explorer and Netscape Navigator. It may also
	include application components that create the page layout.
	</para>

	<para>
	The Application Tier is the "engine" of a web application. It performs
	the business logic; processing user input, making decisions, obtaining
	more data and presenting data to the Presentation Tier to send back to
	the user. The Application Tier may include technology like CGI's, Java,
	.NET services, PHP or ColdFusion, deployed in products like IBM
	WebSphere, WebLogic, JBOSS or ZEND.
	</para>

	<para>
	A Data Tier is used to store things needed by the application and acts
	as a repository for both temporary and permanent data. It is the bank
	vault of a web application. Modern systems are typically now storing
	data in XML format for interoperability with other system and sources.
	</para>

	<para>
	Of course, small applications may consist of a simple C CGI program
	running on a local host, reading or writing files to disk.
	</para>
</sect1>

<sect1>
	<title>
	What Are Web Services?
	</title>

	<para>
	Web Services are receiving a lot of press attention. Some are heralding
	Web Services as the biggest technology breakthrough since the web
	itself; others are more skeptical that they are nothing more than
	evolved web applications.
	</para>

	<para>
	A Web Service is a collection of functions that are packaged as a single
	entity and published to the network for use by other programs. Web
	services are building blocks for creating open distributed systems, and
	allow companies and individuals to quickly and cheaply make their
	digital assets available worldwide. One early example is Microsoft
	Passport, but many others such as Project Liberty are emerging. One Web
	Service may use another Web Service to build a richer set of features to
	the end user. Web services for car rental or air travel are examples. In
	the future applications may be built from Web services that are
	dynamically selected at runtime based on their cost, quality, and
	availability.
	</para>

	<para>
	The power of Web Services comes from their ability to register
	themselves as being available for use using WSDL (Web Services
	Description Language) and UDDI (Universal Description, Discovery
	and Integration).  Web services are based on XML (extensible Markup
	Language) and SOAP (Simple Object Access Protocol).
	</para>

	<para>
	Despite whether you see the difference between sophisticated web
	applications and Web Services, it is clear that these emerging systems
	will face the same security issues as traditional web applications.
	</para>
</sect1>
</chapter>














