<!-- $Id: ch03.xml,v 1.7 2002/09/09 21:35:24 russcoon Exp $ -->
<chapter label="3">
<title>
How Much Security Do You Really Need?
</title>

<sect1>
	<title></title>

	<para>
	When one talks about security of web applications, a prudent question
	to pose is "how much security does this project require?" Software
	is generally created with functionality first in mind and with
	security as a distant second or third. This is an unfortunate
	reality in many development shops. Designing a web application is an
	exercise in designing a system that meets a business need and not
	an exercise in building a system that is just secure for the sake
	of it. However, the application design and development stage is the
	ideal time to determine security needs and build assurance into the
	application. Prevention is better than cure, after all!
	</para>

	<para>
	It is interesting to observe that most security products available
	today are mainly technical solutions that target a specific type
	of issue or problems or protocol weaknesses. They are products
	retrofitting security onto existing infrastructure, including tools
	like application layer firewalls and host/network based Intrusion
	Detection Systems (IDS's).  Imagine a world without firewalls
	(nearly drifted into a John Lennon song there); if there were
	no need to retrofit security, then significant cost savings and
	security benefits would prevail right out of the box.  Of course
	there are no silver bullets, and having multiple layers of security
	(otherwise known as "defense in depth") often makes sense.
	</para>

	<para>
	So how do you figure out how much security is appropriate and needed?
	Well, before we discuss that it is worth reiterating a few important
	points.
	</para>

	<itemizedlist mark="opencircle" spacing="compact">
		<listitem>
			<para>
			Zero risk is not practical
			</para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
			<para>
			There are several ways to mitigate risk
			</para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
			<para>
			Don't spend a million bucks to protect a dime
			</para>
		</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	<para>
	People argue that the only secure host is one that's unplugged.
	Even if that were true, an unplugged host is of no functional use
	and so hardly a practical solution to the security problem. Zero
	risk is neither achievable nor practical. The goal should always
	be to determine what the appropriate level of security is for the
	application to function as planned in its environment. That process
	normally involves accepting risk.
	</para>

	<para>
	The second point is that there are many ways to mitigate risk. While
	this document focuses predominantly on technical countermeasures like
	selecting appropriate key lengths in cryptography or validating user
	input, managing the risk may involve accepting it or transferring it.
	Insuring against the threat occurring or transferring the threat
	to another application to deal with (such as a Firewall) may be
	appropriate options for some business models.
	</para>

	<para>
	The third point is that designers need to understand what they are
	securing, before they can appropriately specify security controls. It is
	all too easy to start specifying levels of security before understanding
	if the application actually needs it. Determining what the core
	information assets are is a key task in any web application
	design process. Security is almost always an overhead, either in
	cost or performance.
	</para>

	<sect2>
		<title>
		What are Risks, Threats and Vulnerabilities?
		</title>

		<para>
		Pronunciation Key
		</para><para>
		risk 
		</para><para>
		(risk)
		</para><para>
		n. 
		</para>

		<orderedlist spacing="compact" numeration="arabic">
			<listitem>
				<para>
				The possibility of suffering harm or loss; danger. 
				</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>
				A factor, thing, element, or course involving
				uncertain danger; a hazard: "the usual risks of
				the desert: rattlesnakes, the heat, and lack of
				water" (Frank Clancy).
				</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<orderedlist spacing="compact" numeration="loweralpha">
					<listitem>
						<para>
						The danger or probability of
						loss to an insurer.
						</para>
					</listitem>

					<listitem>
						<para>
						The amount that an insurance
						company stands to lose.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</orderedlist>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<orderedlist spacing="compact" numeration="loweralpha">
					<listitem>
						<para>
						The variability of returns from
						an investment.
						</para>
					</listitem>

					<listitem>
						<para>
						The chance of nonpayment of a
						debt. 
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</orderedlist>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>
				One considered with respect to the possibility
				of loss: a poor risk.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</orderedlist>

		<para>
		threat
		</para>
		<para>
		n. 
		</para>

		<orderedlist spacing="compact" numeration="arabic">
			<listitem>
				<para>
				An expression of an intention to inflict pain,
				injury, evil, or punishment.
				</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>
				An indication of impending danger or harm. 
				</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>
				One that is regarded as a possible danger; a
				menace.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</orderedlist>

		<para>
		vul-ner-a-ble
		</para><para>
		adj. 
		</para>

		<orderedlist spacing="compact" numeration="arabic">
			<listitem>
				<orderedlist spacing="compact" numeration="loweralpha">
					<listitem>
						<para>
						Susceptible to physical or
						emotional injury.
						</para>
					</listitem>

					<listitem>
						<para>
						Susceptible to attack: "We are
						vulnerable both by water and
						land, without either fleet or
						army" (Alexander Hamilton).
						</para>
					</listitem>

					<listitem>
						<para>
						Open to censure or criticism;
						assailable.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</orderedlist>
				</listitem>

				<listitem>
				<orderedlist spacing="compact" numeration="loweralpha">
					<listitem>
						<para>
						Liable to succumb, as to
						persuasion or temptation.
						</para>
					</listitem>

					<listitem>
						<para>
						Games. In a position to receive
						greater penalties or bonuses in
						a hand of bridge. In a rubber,
						used of the pair of players who
						score 100 points toward game.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</orderedlist>

			</listitem>
		</orderedlist>

		<para>
		An attacker (the "Threat") can exploit a Vulnerability (security
		bug in an application). Collectively this is a Risk.
		</para>
	</sect2>

	<sect2>
		<title>
		Measuring the Risk
		</title>

		<para>
		While we firmly believe measuring risk is more art than science,
		it is nevertheless an important part of designing the overall
		security of a system. How many times have you been asked the
		question "Why should we spend X dollars on this?"  Measuring
		risk generally takes either a qualitative or a quantitative
		approach.
		</para>

		<para>
		A quantitative approach is usually more applicable in the realm
		of physical security or specific asset protection.  Whichever
		approach is taken, however, a successful assessment of the
		risk is always dependent on asking the right questions. The
		process is only as good as its input.
		</para>

		<para>
		A typical quantitative approach as described below can help
		analysts try to determine a dollar value of the assets (Asset
		Value or AV), associate a frequency rate (or Exposure Factor or
		EF) that the particular asset may be subjected to, and
		consequently determine a Single Loss Expectancy (SLE). From an
		Annualized Rate of Occurrence (ARO) you can determine the
		Annualized Loss Expectancy (ALE) of a particular asset and
		obtain a meaningful value for it.
		</para>

		<para>
		Let's explain this in detail:
		</para>

		<para>
		<emphasis role="bold">AV x EF = SLE</emphasis>
		</para>

		<para>
		If our Asset Value is $1000 and our Exposure Factor (%
		of loss a realized threat could have on an asset) is 25% then we
		come out with the following figures:
		</para>

		<para>
		<emphasis role="bold">$1000 x 25% = $250</emphasis>
		</para>

		<para>
		So, our SLE is $250 per incident. To extrapolate that over a
		year we can apply another formula:
		</para>

		<para>
		<emphasis role="bold">SLE x ARO = ALE</emphasis> (Annualized Loss Expectancy)
		</para>

		<para>
		The ALE is the possibility of a specific threat taking place
		within a one-year time frame. You can define your own range,
		but for convenience sake let's say that the range is from 0.0
		(never) to 1.0 (always). Working on this scale an ARO of 0.1
		would indicate that the ARO value is once every ten years. So,
		going back to our formula, we have the following inputs:
		</para>

		<para>
		<emphasis role="bold">SLE ($250) x ARO (0.1) = $25 (ALE)</emphasis>
		</para>

		<para>
		Therefore, the cost to us on this particular asset per annum is
		$25. The benefits to us are obvious, we now have a tangible (or
		at the very least semi-tangible) cost to associate with
		protecting the asset. To protect the asset, we can put a
		safeguard in place up to the cost of $25 / annum.
		</para>

		<para>
		Quantitative risk assessment is simple, eh? Well, sure,
		in theory, but actually coming up with those figures in the
		real world can be daunting and it does not naturally lend
		itself to software principles. The model described before
		was also overly simplified. A more realistic technique
		might be to take a qualitative approach. Qualitative risk
		assessments don't produce values or definitive answers. They
		help a designer or analyst narrow down scenarios and document
		thoughts through a logical process. We all typically undertake
		quantitative analysis in our minds on a regular basis.
		</para>

		<para>
		Typically questions may include:
		</para>

		<itemizedlist mark="opencircle" spacing="compact">
			<listitem>
				<para>
				Do the threats come from external or internal
				parties?
				</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>
				What would the impact be if the software is
				unavailable?
				</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>
				What would be the impact if the system is
				compromised?
				</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>
				Is it a financial loss or one of reputation?
				</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>
				Would users actively look for bugs in the code
				to use to their advantage or can our licensing
				model prevent them from publishing them?
				</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>
				What logging is required?
				</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>
				What would the motivation be for people to
				try to break it (e.g. financial application
				for profit, marketing application for user
				database, etc.)
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para>
		Tools such as the CERIAS CIRDB project
		(https://cirdb.cerias.purdue.edu/website) can significantly
		assist in the task of collecting good information incident
		related costs. The development of threat trees and workable
		security policies is a natural outgrowth of the above questions
		and should be developed for all critical systems.
		</para>

		<para>
		Qualitative risk assessment is essentially not concerned with a
		monetary value but with scenarios of potential risks and ranking
		their potential to do harm. Qualitative risk assessments are
		subjective!
		</para>

	</sect2>

</sect1>
</chapter>



