<chapter id="liberty">
<title>Authentication</title>


<sect1>
<title>What is authentication?</title>
<para>
INSERT ALL MATERIAL FROM V1 OF GUIDE. REMOVE SECTION 6.1.9.8 - SSO ACROSS MULTIPLE DNS DOMAINS
</para>
</sect1>



<sect1>
<title>Single Sign On</title>
<para>
A computer user typically has many online identities to authenticate to many websites or applications. The user is responsible for managing and keeping track of these various identities. The burden can become significant and a security risk. Users use weak passwords that are easy to remember, use the same password on multiple sites, etc. Single sign on technology can remedy this situation. 
</para>

<para>
The most common type of identity management approach is the silo model. In this approach. every application implements its own system based on its specific needs. Larger organizations employ discrete identity management solutions that enable single sign on. Single sign on is a standard way for a user to authenticate to a site and subsequently use other sites without having to authenticate again. My Yahoo, Netscape Netcenter and Amazon are such example. This model is also called a closed community model.
</para>

<para>
There are universal approaches to single sign on: centralized and distributed or federated. 
</para>

<para>
Microsoft Passport is a single sign on service based on a centralized model. Initially Microsoft Passport was a single sign-on solution for Microsoft web sites but later it was made available to third party sites as well.  Microsoft plans to add federation support to Passport in the future.
</para>

<para>
The Liberty Alliance Project is a set of specifications (on which single sign on services can be built) using a federated model. A federated model allows an organization to link its user profile information with a partner's or affiliate. Each maintains its own user information and uses a standard way to share some of this data with their partners for various business purposes. A scenario might be a partnership or a rebate program. 
</para>

<para>
We should note Microsoft Passport and the Liberty Alliance approaches are not mutually exclusive. It is possible for an organization to support either one or both universal approaches in addition to its own custom solution. Such an example is Citigroup.
</para>


<sect2>
<title>Liberty Alliance Project </title>
<para>
The Liberty Alliance is a single sign on specification. The project was partially a response to Microsoft Passport. The project is comprised of many members: Sun, RSA, MasterCard, Visa, SAP, etc. The Liberty Alliance specification is relatively new. Version 1.0 was released in the July 2002 and a revision was added in January 2003. It is not widely deployed yet. Major project members plan to implemented it later in 2003. 
</para>

<sect3>
<title>What does it do?</title>
<para>
An implementation of the Liberty Alliance specifications in its current phase allows for identity federation and authentication or single sign on. Identity federation enables users to do business transactions seamlessly across organizations.
</para>

<para>
The standardized single sign on gives the ability an organization to receive pre-authenticated users from a partner's website. The users will come from a partner organization whom you trust and have an agreement with. 
</para>

<para>
The user is always in control of who can access this information. There are modes of sharing a user can select: always, within a group, per transaction, etc. User consent must be granted for any federation to occur and a user is also able to defederate at any time. The Liberty approach is to privacy is opt-in. 
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3>
<title>How does it work?</title>
<para>
It begins with some business or organizational partners getting to define trust relationships based on Liberty-enabled technology and legal contracts. This federation is known as a circle of trust.

In order to understand the specifications, some terminology will help. The distinct parties in a Liberty enabled system are:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>the user: a consumer that uses the Web </para></listitem>
<listitem><para>service providers : organizations offering Web based services to users. </para></listitem>
<listitem><para>identity providers: service providers offering business incentives so other providers affiliate with them and create a circle of trust.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
So a typical circle of trust consists of one user, one identity provider and one or many service providers. The user must be notified of the information being collected and must grant consent for linking his information.
</para>

<para>
Liberty Alliance uses web standards and protocols, like XML, HTTP. It uses SAML for its authentication token format. SAML messages then use SOAP over HTTP for the standard communication protocol. This in turn is encrypted with TSL or SSL or equivalents such as IPSec. The Liberty specification require confidentiality and integrity from the communication between parties (users, identity providers and service providers).
</para>

<para>
The actual Liberty architecture divided into four modules, each with a specific function. The first two modules have been already completed. The first is the Liberty Identity Federation Framework (ID-FF) and its role is identity federation and management.
</para>

<!--
The ID-FF framework is designed to work with heterogeneous platforms and with all sorts of network devices, from personal computers to mobile phones, PDAs and emerging devices. ID-FF features include:

Opt-in Account Linking, which allows a user with multiple accounts at different Liberty-enabled sites to link the accounts for future authentication and sign-in at those sites 
Simplified Sign-On, allowing a user to sign-on once at a Liberty ID-FF enabled site and to be seamlessly signed-on when navigating at another Liberty- enabled site without the need to authenticate again. Liberty Alliance said simplified single sign-on is supported both within and across circles of trust 
Fundamental Session Management, enabling companies or organizations that link accounts to communicate the type of authentication that should be used when a user signs-on. It also enables global sign-out 
Affiliations, which lets a user choose to federate within a group of affiliated sites 
Anonymity, allowing a service to request certain attributes without needing to know the user's identity 
Protocol for the Real-time Discovery and Exchange of Meta Data, allowing the real-time exchange of meta data (such as X.509 certificates and service endpoints) between Liberty-compliant entities.

-->

<para>
Module 2 is simply the industry  standards which the other modules build upon. These standards and schemas are defined by OASIS, W3C and IETF. These include: SAML, WS-Security, HTTP, WSDL, XML, SOAP, XML-ENC, XML-SIG, SSL/TLS, and WAP. Liberty Alliance is interested in using open standards that enables its functio
</para>

<para>
Module 3 is called the Liberty Identity Web Services Framework (ID-WSF) and as its name applies, it is about creating, identifying and using web identity services. 
</para>

<para>
Module 4 builds on module 3 amd it specifies interopable standards to enable things like alerts, registration, calendar, etc. 
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3>
<title>Why is it important?</title>
<para>
The Liberty Alliance specifications should be considered prior to building a web enabled application. Especially good candidates are intranet or ecommerce web sites. 

The technology can offer some benefits:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>User convenience due to a single user id and password. It produces a  better online experience.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Increased user satisfaction due to better control of identity information and security. Changes of personal information are transparently propagated.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>New levels of personalization due to integration of functionality and services across organizations in a circle of trust.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Enables organizations to create new relationships with each other much faster and at a lower cost.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>There are is no panacea and there are some arguments against this technology:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Risk - it is too recent and unproven.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>As with any technology, there is an initial investment in time and resources.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>It is new and hence not widely deployed. Like a PKI implementation, there is an initial treshold of applications that are able to use certificates to be able to geta great return on investment. Metcalf's Law: The value of a network increases exponentially with the number of nodes. Existing isolated applications are the current standard and will continue to be the majority for the immediate future.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Joining a circle of trust requires a contact in place. Liberty specifications does not make any recommendations and there are some issues still unresolved like liability. What happens if the authenticaton misfires? Who assumes the liability?</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
The value proposition of this technology is primarily interoperability with major identity management systems. Using such a standard will lower costs significantly should your organization partner with a third party in the future. It also allows a standardized single sign on for your organization and its subsidiaries. General Motors is currently testing a Liberty implementation for its intranet application. An employee logged in to the intranet can then go to a 401k website (administered by a third party) 
</para>

<para>
As this technology will become deployed and adopted, we suspect the specification will change somewhat to acomodate real world scenarios. The project has ambitious plans to add more complex services like federated data exchange and B2B transactional support on top of the federation infrastructure.  
</para>

<para>
We are not in a position to recommend the implementation of this technology becuase the decision will involve your organizations' goals, infrastructure, budget, etc.
</para>
</sect3>


<sect3>
<title>How can I use it?</title>
<para>
The Liberty Alliance are a set of specifications, not a product. An organization can either build their application to spec or can purchase an identity management system that is Liberty enabled. Sun and RSA have products available today while HP, Novell will have products shortly. There is also an open source Java toolkit for implementing the Liberty Alliance specification currently in beta. (sourceid.org)

It should be noted that the first phase of the Liberty project does not provide any formal compliance. However, the project is based on open standards so this is not significant issue. 
</para>

<para>
In terms of authentication, their specification states : "Liberty will not prescribe a single technology, protocol, or policy for the processes by which identity providers issue identities to Principals and by which those Principals subsequently authenticate themselves to the identity provider".
<!--  Reference : Liberty Authentication Context Specification, v1.1, page 7, line 120 -->
This means organizations with existing identity management systems don't need replace their systems. 
</para>

<para>
The specification allows gradient levels of authentication within a circle of trust. For example, ff a particular web site or application requires two factor authentication (like smart cards) due to the sensitivity of the data, it will still work very well with other Liberty providers. However, that also means your application supports single sign on only from identity providers that support two factor authentication. 
</para>

<para>
To establish or join a circle of trust a business or operational agreement must be in place. The definition of these agreements are not covered by the Liberty Project and are left solely to the individual parties to negociate.
</para>
</sect3>


<!--
References:

http://www.projectliberty.org/

-->

</sect2>


<sect2>
<title>Microsoft Passport</title>
<para>
INSERT CHAPTER HERE
</para>
</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>SAML</title>
<para>
INSERT CHAPTER HERE
</para>
</sect1>

</chapter>
