<!-- $Id: p3p.xml,v 1.4 2003/04/12 09:54:48 awiesmann Exp $ -->
<chapter id="p3p">
	<chapterinfo>
		<authorgroup>
			<author>
				<firstname>Tim</firstname>
				<surname></surname>
			</author>
		</authorgroup>
	</chapterinfo>

	<title>Web Application and Browser based Privacy</title>

	<sect1 id="getting-personal">
		<title>Getting Personal about Privacy </title>
		<para>
If you're anything like me, there would be many occasions that you have clicked the 'register now' button before completing an Internet based transaction without first reading the sites Privacy Policy. Each time you do this, you increase the chances of the information you have left behind being used as Spam against you. </para>

		<para>
If you do this, you're not alone! Most people registering their personal details on web sites do so without any regard to the Privacy Policy that states how their information may be used. This may be because no one really likes to read what is perceived to be a legalese dull document or simply because we are in such a hurry to purchase the goods that we don't want another hurdle in our way. The fact that these web sites could be using cookies to track our spending habits and the way we navigate the site and, more importantly, selling this information to 3rd parties doesn't seem to register with the average punter. 
</para>

		<para>
So from a personal perspective, we should be more aware of how our information is being used (or re-used) and the main purpose of this document is to outline the standard that will help us the most; The Platform for Privacy Preferences (P3P). But why should companies themselves be concerned? Why, as a company should I bother going through this process? Well, there are a number of reasons but probably two main ones, outlined below:
</para>



		<sect2>
			<title>Client Retention</title>
			<para>
A clearly stated Privacy Policy sends a positive message to the consumer. We take your data seriously and this is how we protect it. This is how you opt-out if you don't like it. Once mutual trust is established, client retention is increased. With the advent of I.E. 6.0 and Netscape 7 which both include a P3P user agent, you may find your site being blocked by the browser if the client has been stringent with the sites he wishes to access.
</para>
		</sect2>


		<sect2>
			<title>Privacy Related Legislation</title>
			<para>
The Government is reacting to consumers concerns over Privacy. The most obvious areas are those covered by the GLBA and HIPAA but there were also more than 5000 consumer privacy bills introduced in state legislature in 2000 with a further 6900 in 2001. Additionally, 39 states have introduced one or more privacy laws.
Privacy is big news in all areas of the World (with some notable exceptions). In Australia, The Privacy Act 2001 was passed in December 2001 with further updates in December 2002. The Act, modelled on the National Privacy Principals (NPP's) was modelled on guidelines originally put forward by the Organization (OECD). The high level principles organization was one of the founders of setting Privacy guidelines since 1980.
The OECD is quite pertinent here and is something that will come up as we discuss in more detail the main thrust of this section; P3P.
</para>
		</sect2>

	</sect1>

	<sect1>
		<title>The Platform for Privacy Preferences (P3P)</title>
		<para>
The project itself is run by the World Wide Consortium (W3C). The first W3C recommended release - P3P 1.0, was published on the 16th April 2002 initially to a fair amount of criticism. The principles for this standard have been around for many yers prior to the official W3C recommendation and a number of the critcisms are really a hangover of earlier dicussions. A recent meeting by the W3C in November 2002 will see the release of P3P 1.1 later this year that addresses some of shortfalls of P3P 1.0 with some other more major additions that will be added in P3P 2.0. More details on these changes and additions are discussed within this chapter.
</para>

		<para>
Regardless of the version, the P3P project is there to enable the user to make informed decisions about when their personal information should be revealed in an automated way as opposed to trawling through the legalese and loopholes of a policy statement. Perhaps the major endorsement has come with P3P support within Microsoft's Internet Explorer 6.0; now essentially the default standard for browsing has the P3P client built-in. There are also a number of other clients which will be discussed in this chapter, and they all have there place but the tried and tested method of embedding the technology within a tool that 80% of Internet users use is a surefire way of success.
</para>

		<para>
This chapter looks at the P3P 1.0 specifications itself as well as outlining some of the enhancements and major bugbears that will be fixed in upcoming releases. Specifically, this section will cover the following:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>The fundamentals of privacy</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>A brief history of P3P development</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>How P3P works and some of the more pertinent tools</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>How to deploy P3P policies on your site and some of the issues with Compact Policies</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>The future of P3P</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para>
Privacy is a much overused term; it seems to be used almost as loosely as the term industry best practices or ROI or any of the other acronyms that we use, particulalry in the IT industry. Imagine if there was a nice acroynym for Privacy, we can't just call it "P" - well, if nothing else P3P gives us an acronym we can drop into conversation!
</para>

		<para>
Jokes aside, Privacy is essentially the freedom from unwanted intruders into our daily lives. So, to protect our Privacy we need a mechanism to keep the intruders out. To do that, we need to know where our personal information is going, who has access to it, who can modify, alter or destruct it. In short, we want to have a good idea as to how the information that is "us" is used or abused.
</para>

		<para>
Theoretically, we have guaranteed First Ammendment rights to privacy - the reality in the Internet World can be somewhat contradictory to this basic right. Who has the right to use information against us? Are there precedents where we don't want people to have privacy? Case in point was a web site that turned out to be the largest commercial child-porn operation ever uncovered in 1999. In a raid by law enforcement officials, computers were seized that held information on over 250,000 paying subscribers. These details were then forwarded to law enforcement agencies around the globe and a large number of arrests were made. Did these people deserve Privacy? Let's move on...
</para>

		<para>
Ultimately it's 'data' we're talking about: data defines who we are, what our likes and dislikes are. A misuse of this defining data is when this information that defines us is used in different context and without our consent or indeed is garnered at the inital onset without our consent. How many sites are there that give you a usable method of accessing them if you really don't want to share personal information? Not many.
</para>

		<para>
As a webmaster and business owner, this also comes back to Client Retention mentioned at the head of this chapter. In recent times there has been a lot of bad press associated with software with Spyware installed; applications that filter back potentially personal information unbeknownst to the user. In fact, an early critiscism voiced back in 1998 by the EU against P3P was that it didn't do enough to protect users privacy. The ensuing outcry resulted in a partial re-write to lessen the amount of 'behind the scenes' chatter between P3P agents and web servers. 
</para>

		<para>
There are numerous surveys that have been undertaken by many organisations on privacy. Probably the most pertinent being those conducted or collated by PrivacyExchange.org. Based on a wide reaching survey, 29% said they trust sites that sell products or services online and only 33% said they trust web sites that provide advice about such purchases. That is incredibly low compared to the 58% who say they trust newspaper and television news so we're talking about reliability of information here - and reliability goes hand in hand with trust which is the backbone of privacy.
Most users will not read online privacy policies carefully, just 3%, although they are more likely to read them if they are entering their credit card details or social security numbers.
</para>

		<para>
In all the surveys, the importance of privacy is highlighted. There are various analysts estimates on the value of the amount of retail sales lost due to privacy concerns - ranging from $5 billion to $25 billion. The reality probably lies somewhere in the middle but which ever way you look at it it's a significant amount of lost revenue.
</para>

		<para>
So, as a web user who wants to access information or engage in an online purchase what sort of answers to I want from the web site? The main ones are outlined below:
</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>How do web sites use my information when I sign up as a member or to buy something?</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>What information do web sites collect about me?</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>How do I know my information is secure and stays secure?</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para>
There are various mechanisms that web sites can use to track informtaion on us and our movements. We will discuss some of these surveillance methods then get onto to the current state of play with privacy technology solutions.
Then we will look at the privacy solutions offered by the current technologies. 
</para>

		<para>
All browsers and web server logs can trap a huge amount of information including the type of OS we're using, browser type, IP address, referring page and cookies. This information can be used to build up a user profile which advertisers in particular find most interesting.
Within the HTTP header, a field called 'Referer' identifies the URL associated with the requested page. In other words, we know where you've just been. Web sites use this to gather user habits as well as a method of tracking how successful online advertising is being at other sites. The logs on the server can then store the URL of the originating request for further analysis. If the GET method within HTTP is used it sends the values in the URL in name-value pairs, visible in clear text. This enables me to look through my logs looking for personal details which could include credit card details, username, age - basically any information I've submitted.
</para>
	</sect1>



	<sect1>
		<title>Cookies</title>
		<para>
There are other sections in this book that discuss cookies in more detail, particularly how to subvert and generally mis-use informtaion so only a basic decription is given here. A cookie is a unique identifier that a web server places directly on your computer. Look on it as a  serial number that may be used to retrieve your records from a web sites database. It's usually a string of random-looking letters long enough to be unique. 
</para>

		<para>
Cookies really came about to try and add some 'state' information to requests. As HTTP is stateless, there is nothing to link one request with another. Cookies where therefore designed to extend the protocol to allow web sites to send state information to the browser which may be queried by the server at a later date.
</para>

		<para>
Cookies are useful and in their intended form enable a form of continuity to be established with the browser. They greatly simplify web application development and allow the web server to identify returning users giving them the profile they setup on their first visit to the web site.
</para>

		<para>
With this functionality comes some danger for the cookie illiterate; they can track a users movements around a web site without their knowledge - in some cases this can be used to track users across multiple web sites.
</para>

		<para>
As stated, detailed information on cookies can be found in other sections within this book detailing session, permanent and first-party cookies, but probably the worse case scenario are those that hold personal information that can be accessed by another web site. Some sites even use cookies to store credit card informtaion (or at least link to that informtation - a very bad thing.
</para>
	</sect1>



	<sect1>
		<title>Technical Privacy Solutions</title>
		<para>
In this section we will explore some of the technical and non-technical methods that web sites should deploy to ensure users privacy. this will also give you some things to look out for when visiting a web site.
</para>

		<para>
Each web site could declare its privacy policy describing the sweb sites privacy practices. The presence of such a policy should help users make an informed decision as to whether they wish to engage with the web site, and they can then make a decision as to whether to opt in or out. 
According tomost privacy surveys, the presence of a privacy policy increases user confidence and retention in the site. Such policies are often written in natural language text (like English). A number of policies, however are difficult to understand and use wildly differing formats. 
</para>

		<para>
As discussed, P3P provides an XML-based description of the privacy policy pertaining to the web site. B using standards-based approaches to define policy, automated agents are able to read the policies and act on the users' behalf based on their preferences thus taking the manual pain away from the user.
There are also a number of Privacy Certification Programs Seal programs run and promoted by privacy agencies for compliance with a stated policy. Such programs use independent auditors who certify that the site is compliant with their stated privacy policies. These programs also specify a complaint process and specify how disputes can be resolved. BBBOnline, TRUSTe, and CPA Webtrust are some of the better know seal programs. The web sites that employ these certifications contain their logos and in most cases, with the added exposure of privacy concerns, give the user a level of confidence which can be noted by client retention.
</para>
	</sect1>



	<sect1>
		<title>Privacy Laws and Organizations</title>
		<para>
Privacy laws and regulatory bodies play an important role in the privacy landscape, as they are the enforcing agencies. However, the Internet encompasses every part of the world, and the law is different in various parts 
of the world. The US has a lot of laws like the Freedom of Information Act, Children's Online Privacy Protection Act (COPPA), and so on. These laws focus on increasing the transparency and fairness in Internet transactions. COPPA requires parental consent before collecting personal information from Children.
Australia has the Privacy Act 2001 as outlined in the beginning of this section and the EU has the Data Protection Directive which prohibits the secondary use of data without the clients consent.
</para>

		<para>
Let's get into P3P in more detail. We've discussed the protocol from a high level but how does it actually work? Well, P3P is a machine readable vocabulary and syntax for expressing a  web sites data management practices. P3P enabled browsers and applications read the syntax and comare against the users stated preferences and, importantly, inform the user when these policies to not conform to their preferences.
P3P vocabularly means:
</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>Who is collecting data and what data is being collected</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>What will the data be used for</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Opt-in/out options</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Are there external data recipients</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>What is the data retention policy</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>How are disputes on the policy resolved</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Location of human readable policy</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para>
An example of a P3P Policy showing the XML encoding is detailed below:
</para>

		<screen>
			<![CDATA[
<POLICY name="mysite"
discuri="http://www.mysite.com/PrivacyPolicy.html">
<ENTITY>
<DATA-GROUP>
<DATA  ref="business.name">mysite</DATA>
<DATA ref="business.contact.info.postal.street">200 Bangalore Avenue</DATA>
<DATA ref="business.contact.info.city">Bangalore</DATA>
<DATA ref="business.contact.info.country">Asutralia</DATA>
<DATA ref="business.comtact.info.telecom.telephone.number">32334333</DATA>
</DATA-GROUP>
</ENTITY>
<ACCESS><nonident/></ACCESS>
<DISPUTES-GROUP>
<DISPUTES>
resolution-type="independant"
service="http://www.bbbonline.org"
<REMEDIES><correct/></REMEDIES>
</DISPUTES>
</DISPUTES-GROUP>
<STATEMENT><br/><PURPOSE><admin/><develop/></PURPOSE>
<RECIPIENT><ours/><</RECIPIENT>
<RETENTION><no-retention/></RETENTION>
<DATA-GROUP>
<DATA ref="#dynamic.clickstream"/>
<DATA ref="#dynamic.http"/>
</DATA-GROUP>
</STATEMENT?
</POLICY>

]]></screen>

		<para>
This is by no means an exhaustive list of all the syntax but it highlights some of the major areas. There are other entries that can explicitely state which areas are actually covered by the privacy policy and also exclusion can be made in certain areas. The POLICY is the root tag that holds the policy document itself. The discuri attribute is very important; this defines where the natural language policy is located. 
</para>

		<para>
The ACCESS element indicates if the site allows users to access their identified information. The value  
			<![CDATA[<nonident/>]]> indicates that the site does not collect identified data.
</para>

		<para>
The ENTITY tag decribes the legal entity, generally including the business name and adress. 
</para>

		<para>
The DISPUTES-GROUP can contain several DISPUTE resolutions. The above example refers to the BBBOnline seal program as a dipsutes resolution body.
</para>

		<para>
The REMEDIES element denotes how a breach in policy would be corrected. The 
			<![CDATA[<correct/>]]> tag indicates that the site will remedy the correction of any wrongul breaches.
</para>

		<para>
The RETENTION element indicates how long data is retained for. The 
			<![CDATA[<no-retention/>]]> tag indicates that the site only retains information for the brief period it takes to undergo the transaction.
</para>

		<para>
Of course, we need user agents to interprate these P3P policies. One of the first to arrive was embedded within Microsofts I.E. 6.0 although agents were available as plug in for previous versions. Development is also taking place with PDA's, wireless devices and cellular phones.
</para>


		<para>
If you're using I.E. 6.0 you may see a warning appear when the browser encounters a cookie that either doesn't have a compact policy or contravenes the users preferences, highlighted below:
</para>
		<mediaobject>
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata fileref="images/privacy_pic2.png" format="PNG"/>
			</imageobject>
		</mediaobject>

		<para>
By clicking on the warning icon you can see privacy report:
</para>
		<mediaobject>
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata fileref="images/privacy_pic3.png" format="PNG"/>
			</imageobject>
		</mediaobject>

		<para>
Clicking on the summary button would then detail the policy for review:
</para>
		<mediaobject>
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata fileref="images/privacy_pic4.png" format="PNG"/>
			</imageobject>
		</mediaobject>


		<para>
		To alter a users preferences in I.E. 6.0, you can change the privacy settings in the privacy slide bar:
		</para>

		<mediaobject>
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata fileref="images/privacy_pic5.png" format="PNG"/>
			</imageobject>
		</mediaobject>
		

		<para>
Before we move on, a few words should be said on compact policies. Compact policies enable the P3P policies to be set completely in the HTTP header when cookies are set using the SET_COOKIE directive. It's important to note that comacy policies only reflect information regarding to cookies and hence do not represent all the individual fields that can be defined in a full policy. There are a few shortfalls in the compact policy. They cannot specify an expiry tag and assume that the policy is valid through the lifecycle of the cookie itself. Therefore changing the policy associated with a cookie can be problematic. It may be neccessary to stop setting cookies using the first cookie name, stop gathering information that is gathered from the first cookie and then begin setting a new cookie with the associated updated Compact Policy. Also, there is no caching of the compact policy by the user agent so the server always sends this policy.
</para>
	</sect1>



	<sect1>
		<title>Preparing for a P3P Implementation</title>
		<para>
This section highlights some of the areas that must be considered before deploying P3P policies. 
</para>

		<sect2>
			<title>Implement a Human Readable Policy</title>
			<para>
The initial time spent on this stage is certainly time well spent and will ease the ultimate aim, the implementation of P3P. 
You need to determine the sources of consumer data that you collate or need to collate, determine who it is shared with, the retention period and how the data itself is secured.
Get agreement with all parts of the business that handle consumer data - remember that not all sides will inreact via online mechanisms. How do you currently deal with consumer data?
Develop your policy and publish it on your web site - make sure you educate your employees and partners on the policy.
</para>
		</sect2>

		<sect2>
			<title>Audit your web site before P3P implementation</title>
			<para>
Any review that you do before implementation will save you time in the long run. Remember, you may end up with a number of different P3P policies. One may relate to competitions, another to online shopping and perhaps another to cover areas where no data is retained. The online shopping policy may have the capability to opt-out for example.
</para>
			<para>
Remember, anything that has a URI can have a P3P policy associated with it. Make a note of which URI's would require a P3P policy associated with them and hence how many P3P policies you need to develop.
Have a look at http://www.w3.org/p3pdeployment for an idea on how many policies to create for your site.
</para>
		</sect2>

		<sect2>
			<title>Topics Addressed by P3P</title>
			<para>
Remember the areas that are particularly pertinent for your P3P policies:
</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>Identity and contact informtion of your company</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>P3P files location</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Access Policy</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Disputes Policy</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Remedies available for any issues</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Type of data collected</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Purpose of data collection</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Recipients of the data</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Retention Policy</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>

			<para>
Clarification of all these areas will mean you are well prepared for when it comes to actually implement the policies as they form the basis of the policy. Gather input form your Human Readable Policy as well. Think in terms of the key elements outlined previously such as RETENTION, DATA-GROUP and DISPUTES.
</para>
		</sect2>



		<sect2>
			<title>Create P3P files with a P3P Generator</title>
			<para>
There are now many tools to enable you to do this. As with all tools, none are perfect in interprating your unique requirements. Perhaps the best place tp find the latest P3P Generator Tools is http://www.p3ptoolbox.org. Make sure you review the output thoroughly. Some files will be created in XML, others in HTML and Compacty Policies are just short strings of text.
Use a P3P validator such as the one located at http://www.w3.org/validator. This tool is extremely useful for evaluating your P3P policies and highlighting any errors.
</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>


	<sect1>
		<title>Summary</title>
		<para>
By implementing P3P your organisation is taking a vital step in the general evolution of web based services. You are sending a clear message to your consumers that you take their data seriously and clearly outline what you may do with the data they entrust you with. Privacy is one of the major hurdles to overcome in particular with ecommerce to enable a stronger Internet economy.
</para>

		<para>
Remember though that P3P is not a silver bullet as far as privacy is concerned; it's a framework, albeit a very important one and certainly the method that has the most momentum at this point in time. To truly get the teeth to back up P3P, legislation is required. Some sites do very well out of gathering and onselling users details so we can't rely on a self regulated technology alone.
Treat P3P as it is intended; you run a reputable web site and you want to tell everyone that you do so. This is exactly why some of the heavyweights carry P3P polices such as Microsoft, IBM and HP amongst many others.
</para>

		<para>
As P3P evolves alongside more stringent privacy legislation it pays to deploy P3P in a timely manner rather than waiting for precednts to be set. Also, with P3P user agents now resident in I.E. 6.0 and Netscape 7.0 you may find your site being excluded by users simply because you don't have a P3P policy.
</para>

		<para>
The advice - get on the program now, make the positive statement to your client base and stay one step ahead!
</para>

	</sect1>
</chapter>



