<!-- $Id: privacy.xml,v 1.5 2003/04/03 13:55:59 awiesmann Exp $ -->
<chapter id="ch12">
	<title>Privacy Considerations</title>

	<para>
	This section deals with user privacy. Systems that deal with private
	user information such as social security numbers, addresses, telephone
	numbers, medical records or account details typically need to take
	additional steps to ensure the users' privacy is maintained. In some
	countries and under certain circumstances there may be legal or
	regulatory requirements to protect users' privacy.
	</para>

	<sect1>
		<title>The Dangers of Communal Web Browsers</title>

		<para>
		All systems should clearly and prominently warn users of the
		dangers of sharing common PC's such as those found in Internet
		Cafes or libraries. The warning should include appropriate
		education about:
		</para>

		<itemizedlist mark="opencircle" spacing="compact">
			<listitem>
				<para>
				the possibility of pages being retained in the
				browser cache
				</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>
				a recommendation to log out and close the
				browser to kill session cookies
				</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>
				the fact that temp files may still remain
				</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>
				the fact that proxy servers and other LAN users
				may be able to intercept traffic
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para>
		Sites should not be designed with the assumption that any
		part of a client is secure, and should not make assumptions
		about the integrity.
		</para>
	</sect1>

	<sect1>
		<title>Using personal data</title>

		<para>
		Systems should take care to ensure that personal data is
		displayed only where absolutely needed. Account numbers,
		birth names, login names, social security numbers and other
		specific identifying personal data should always be masked (if
		an account number is 123456789 the application should display
		the number as *****6789) unless absolutely needed. First
		names or nicknames should be used for birth names, and numeric
		identifiers should display a subset of the complete string.
		</para>

		<para>Where the data is needed the pages should:</para>

		<itemizedlist mark="opencircle" spacing="compact">
			<listitem>
				<para>
				set pages to pre-expire
				</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>
				set the no-cache meta tags
				</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>
				set the no-pragma-cache meta tags
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</sect1>

	<sect1>
		<title>Enhanced Privacy Login Options</title>

		<para>
		Systems can offer an "enhanced privacy" login option.  When
		users login with "enhanced privacy", all pages subsequently
		served to the user would:
		</para>

		<itemizedlist mark="opencircle" spacing="compact">
			<listitem>
				<para>set pages to pre-expire</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>set the no-cache meta tags</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>set the no-pragma-cache meta tags</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>use SSL or TLS</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para>
		This offers users a great deal of flexibility when using trusted
		hosts at home or traveling.
		</para>
	</sect1>

	<sect1>
		<title>Browser History</title>

		<para>
		Systems should take care to ensure that sensitive data is not
		viewable in a user's browser history.
		</para>

		<itemizedlist mark="opencircle" spacing="compact">
			<listitem>
				<para>
				All form submissions should use a POST request.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</sect1>
</chapter>
