<!-- $Id: about_owasp.xml,v 1.1 2004/02/13 14:39:45 awiesmann Exp $ -->

<sect1>
	<title>About The Open Web Application Security Project</title>
	<para>
	The Open Web Application Security Project (OWASP) was started in 
	September 2001 by Mark Curphey and now has over 40 active contributors from around the world. 
	OWASP is a "not for profit" open source reference point for system architects, developers, 
	vendors, consumers and security professionals involved in Designing, Developing, Deploying 
	and Testing the security of web applications and Web Services. In short, the Open Web Application 
	Security Project aims to help everyone and anyone build more secure web applications and Web Services. 
	OWASP projects are broadly divided into two main categories, development projects and documentation projects. 
	</para>
	<para>
	Our development projects currently consist of WebScarab - a web application vulnerability assessment 
	suite including proxy tools, Filters - generic security boundary filters that developers can use in their own applications, 
	CodeSeeker - an commercial quality application level firewall and Intrusion Detection System that runs on Windows and Linux and supports IIS, Apache and iPlanet web servers, 
	WebGoat - an interactive training and benchmarking tool that users can learn about web application security 
	in a safe and legal environment and the OWASP Portal - our own Java based portal code designed with security 
	as a prime concern. We are also developing a Model View Controller framework for the .NET platform. 
	All software and documentation is open source under the GNU Public License and 
	copyrighted to the Free Software Foundation so that the community can contribute without the fear of exploitation. 
	</para>
	<para>
	Our documentation projects currently consist of this Guide and Testing - a web site security testing methodology 
	and framework.
	</para>
	<para>
	We also have one significant project that spans both our development projects and documentation 
	projects called VulnXML. VulnXML is an XML file format for describing web application security 
	vulnerabilities, which can be used in a number of commercial and open source tools to check for specific 
	problems. OWASP has developed a web based VulnXML database where the community can submit checks, which are QA'd
	by the OWASP team before being released into a production feed.
	</para>
</sect1>

