<!-- $Id: what_are_webservices.xml,v 1.1 2004/02/13 14:39:45 awiesmann Exp $ -->

<sect1>
	<title>
	What Are Web Services?
	</title>

        <para>
        Web Services have received a lot of press and with that comes
        a great deal of confusion over what they really are.  Some are
        heralding Web Services as the biggest technology breakthrough
        since the web itself; others are more skeptical that they are
        nothing more than evolved web applications.  In either case,
        the issues of web application security apply to web services
        just as they do to web applications.
        </para>

        <para>
        At the simplest level, web services can be seen as a
        specialized web application that differ mainly at the
        presentation tier level.  While web applications typically are
        HTML based, web services are XML based.  Web applications are
        normally accessed by users, while web service are employed as
        building blocks by other web applications.  Web services are
        typically based on a small number of functions, while web
        applications tend to deal with a broader set of features.
        </para>

	<para>
	A Web Service is a collection of functions that are packaged
	as a single entity and published to the network for use by
	other programs. Web services are building blocks for creating
	open distributed systems, and allow companies and individuals
	to quickly and cheaply make their digital assets available
	worldwide. One Web Service may use another Web Service to
	build a richer set of features to the end user. In the future
	applications may be built from Web services that are
	dynamically selected at runtime based on their cost, quality,
	and availability.
	</para>

	<para>
	The power of Web Services comes from their ability to register
	themselves as being available for use using WSDL (Web Services
	Description Language) and UDDI (Universal Description,
	Discovery and Integration).  Web services are based on XML
	(extensible Markup Language) and SOAP (Simple Object Access
	Protocol). Web services allow one application to communicate
	with another using standards based technology and build richer
	applications.
	</para>

	<mediaobject>
		<imageobject>
			<imagedata fileref="need a good web services diagram" format="JPEG"/>
		</imageobject>
		<textobject>
		<phrase>The Web Services Technology Stack</phrase>
		</textobject>
	</mediaobject>

	<para>
        Whether your focus is on securing web services themselves or
        as a component within a larger web application, the same
        security issues faced by traditional web applications are
        present in web services as well.
	</para>
</sect1>
