<!-- $Id: introduction.xml,v 1.3 2004/08/03 12:13:14 awiesmann Exp $ -->
<sect1>
        <title>What's in This Section?</title>
        <para>
        The Security Techniques section provides an overview of the security-related techniques, which are used within the development of web applications and web services. It contains Best Practices about Input Validation, Logging, and Session Management. Besides these practice-oriented chapters this section also contains information concerning Cryptography, Authentication (SAML), and Transport Security technologies like SSL and SSH.
        </para>
        <para>
        This section starts with a chapter containing an explanation of Authentication and a description of the SAML protocol.
        </para>
        <para>
        The second chapter is about Session Management, how it works and what the pitfalls are. Sessions are quite important to store user information since HTTP is a stateless protocol and web applications often need a way to store user information.
        </para>
        <para>
        Before delving into Transport Security, the Crypto chapter gives an overview about cryptography and what crypto is for. It also has some discussion about common pitfalls to avoid.
        </para>
        <para>
        Transport Security is the fourth chapter. It explains transport security motivations, the tools and technologies available and how they should be used. It references additional detail which can be found in the Crypto chapter.
        </para>
        <para>
        One of the biggest problems with Web Applications is discussed in the Input Validation chapter. It features some examples of how to avoid pitfalls while developing applications and contains mitigation strategies to defeat cross-site scripting injections and other exploits caused by bad input.
        </para>
        <para>
        The last chapter is about Logging. While logs are normally not considered very important, this chapter contains a few thoughts and best practices about how and why logging is important and how it should be done.
        </para>
</sect1>

