<!-- $Id: session_management.xml,v 1.8 2004/05/11 21:06:24 awiesmann Exp $ -->
<sect1>
	<title>Introduction</title>
	<para>
	Normal applications have the innate ability to work with local data ("state") 
	which is held by the operating system for the duration of the program's run, 
	such as global, heap and stack variables. This is not how web applications work; 
	the web server serves up pages in response to client requests. By design, the web 
	server is free to forget everything about pages it has rendered in the past as 
	there's no explicit state. 
	</para>
	<para>
	This works well when rendering static content, such as a brochure or image, but 
	not so well when you want to do real work, such as filling out a form or if you 
	have multiple users you need to keep separate, such as in an online banking 
	application.
	</para>
	<para>
	Web servers are extended by application frameworks, such as J2EE or ASP.NET, 
	implementing a state management scheme tying individual user's requests into a 
	"session" by tying a cryptographically unique random value stored in a cookie 
	(or elsewhere within client submitted data) against state held on the server, 
	thus giving users the appearance of a stateful web-based application. Being able 
	to separate and recognize each user's actions to specific sessions is critical 
	to web security.
	</para>
	<para>
	Although most users of this guide will be using an application framework with 
	built in session management capabilities, others will use languages such as 
	Perl CGI which do not. They are at an immediate disadvantage as they have to 
	re-invent the wheel for no good reason. In the author's experience with source 
	reviews and penetration tests, these implementations are invariably weak and 
	breakable. Another very common mistake is to implement a weak session management 
	scheme on top of a strong one. It is theoretically possible to write and use a 
	cryptographically secure session management scheme, which is the focus of this 
	chapter. However, for mere mortals, it cannot be stressed highly enough to use 
	an application framework which has adequate session management. There is no 
	value in re-writing such basic building blocks.
	</para>
	<para>
	Application frameworks such as J2EE, PHP, ASP and ASP.NET take care of much of 
	the low level session management details and allow fine level control at a 
	programmatic level, rather than at a server configuration level. For example, 
	ASP.NET uses an encrypted "view state" mechanism, which renders as a hidden 
	field in each page. This view state can be used to transmit variables, web 
	control locations, and so on. Using programmatic means, it's possible to 
	include or exclude a variable from the view state, particularly if you don't 
	need the state to be available between different pages of the same application. 
	This can save download time, reduce bandwidth, and improve execution times.
	</para>
	<para>
	Careful management of the view state is the difference between a well optimized 
	application, and one that "just works."
	</para>
	<sect2>
		<title>Session authentication</title>
		<para>
		Session management is by its nature closely tied to authentication, 
		but this does not mean users should be considered authenticated until the 
		web application has taken positive action to tie a session with a trusted 
		credential or other authentication token.
		</para>
		<para>
		For example, just connecting to a PHP application will issue every end user 
		with a PHPSessionID cookie, but that does not mean that users should be 
		trusted or you should ship them goods. Only once they have proven that they 
		are known to your web application should they be trusted, and even then.
		</para>
		<para>
		Typically, the average web application will present the user with a logon 
		page or field. The user authenticates with the application by filling in 
		the form. The application processes the logon request, and if successful, 
		ties the session ID with the credential by either maintaining a small cache 
		of state on the web server (typical of application frameworks), or by sending 
		down some identifying session token to the end user's browser. To the end 
		user, this appears as being "logged on" to the application as they no longer 
		have to manually assert their credentials to the application on each page they 
		use. For most users, this is all they care about, but there are many traps for 
		the unwary web developer.
		</para>
	</sect2>
	<sect2>
		<title>Cookies</title>
		<para>
		Love 'em or loathe them, cookies are now a prerequisite to use many online 
		banking and e-commerce sites. Cookies were never designed to store secrets, 
		such as usernames and passwords or any sensitive information, but were 
		instead initially used to hold information such as the last visit time or 
		user preferences. Web developers need to understand this design decision 
		as it is helpful in understanding how to minimize the risk of use of 
		cookies and other session objects.
		</para>
		<para>
		Cookies were originally introduced by Netscape and are now specified in 
		RFC 2965 (superseding RFC 2109), with RFC 2964 and BCP44 offering guidance 
		on best practice. There are several categories of cookies:
		</para>
		<itemizedlist mark="opencircle" spacing="compact">
			<listitem>
				<para>Persistent and Secure</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Persistent and Non-Secure</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Non-Persistent and Secure</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Non-Persistent and Non-Secure</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<sect3>
			<title>Persistent vs. Non-Persistent</title>
			<para>
			Persistent cookies are stored in a text file (cookies.txt under 
			Netscape and multiple *.txt files for Internet Explorer) on the 
			client and are valid until the cookie's expiry date falls due. 
			Non-Persistent cookies are stored in RAM on the client and are 
			destroyed when the browser is closed or the cookie is explicitly 
			killed by a log-off script. However, this does not mean that 
			non-persistent cookies are safe; any information obtained from the 
			client should be treated with care.
			</para>
		</sect3>
		<sect3>
			<title>Secure vs. Non-Secure</title>
			<para>
			Secure cookies can only be sent over HTTPS (SSL). Non-Secure cookies 
			can be sent over HTTPS or regular HTTP. The title of secure is 
			somewhat misleading. It only enforces transport security for the 
			cookie. Any data sent to the client should be considered under the 
			total control of the end user, regardless of the transport mechanism 
			in use.
			</para>
		</sect3>
		<sect3>
			<title>How do Cookies work?</title>
			<para>
			Cookies enable a server and browser to pass information among 
			themselves, even between reboots if persistent cookies are used. As 
			discussed above, HTTP is stateless. Setting a cookie is like marking 
			a client with a rubber stamp, saying "show this to me next time you 
			ask for a page."
			</para>
			<para>
			But this persistent marking presents a problem if two people use
			the same client computer, they share the same cookies. This is 
			particularly troublesome when using online banking applications at 
			Internet cafes, or worse, when sending romantic messages to a 
			personals site when your wife is around. Surprisingly many web 
			applications do not think about this shared exposure, and yet its 
			solution a logout button which clears the session state is 
			painfully obvious.
			</para>
			<para>
			In an effort to protect your privacy, the original implementation of 
			cookies made it such that cookies are not shared across DNS domains. 
			When everything works to plan, Domain A (say evilattacker.com) can't 
			read or write to Domain B's (say bank.com's) cookies. This also extends 
			to URL paths in the same domain; for example, www.example.com/foo/ 
			can not read or write to www.example.com/blah/ cookies. This can present 
			a problem to a web application nested in the server's directory 
			hierarchy to read cookies from other hierarchies unless the cookies are 
			defined as usable domain wide, although for many people who share the 
			same web server this is actually a blessing. Note that there have been 
			cookie handling vulnerabilities in most popular web clients, 
			particularly in relation to DNS and directory restrictions, so don't 
			expect cookies to be completely safe, even when you're doing exactly the 
			right thing. Remember, by design, cookies are not for secrets.
			</para>
			<para>
			Cookies can be set using two main methods: HTTP headers and JavaScript. 
			The server method sends a Cookie HTTP header to the client, and the client 
			remembers this according to the cookie's parameters. This header tells the 
			client to add this information to the client's cookies file or store the 
			information in RAM. Alternatively, using JavaScript is becoming a popular 
			way to set and read cookies as some "security" proxies will filter out 
			cookies in the HTTP header. JavaScript on the other hand can be deactivated 
			in the user's browser and a script setting or reading such a cookie will 
			therefore never work.
			</para>
			<para>
			Once a cookie is set, all page requests to the cookie domain (the URL and 
			any trailing path) from the user's browser will include the cookie 
			information set by the server's previous response.
			</para>
		</sect3>
		<sect3>
			<title>What's in a cookie?</title>
			<para>
			The content of a cookie is at the total discretion of the developer, but 
			that only lasts until the client gets it. Once a client has the cookie 
			contents, they can change it in any way they like, which is a very popular 
			attack technique.
			</para>
			<para>
			A typical cookie used to store a session token (owasp.org for example) 
			looks much like: Table 13-1. Structure Of A Cookie The columns below 
			illustrate the six parameters that can be stored in a cookie:
			</para>
			<itemizedlist mark="opencircle" spacing="compact">
				<listitem>
					<para>domain:</para>
					<para>The website domain that created and that can read the variable.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>flag:</para>
					<para>
					A TRUE/FALSE value indicating whether all machines 
					within a given domain can access the variable.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>path:</para>
					<para>
					The path attribute supplies a URL range for which 
					the cookie is valid. If path is set to /reference, 
					the cookie will be sent for URLs in /reference as 
					well as sub-directories such as/reference/web 
					protocols. A pathname of " / " indicates that the 
					cookie will be used for all URLs at the site from 
					which the cookie originated.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>secure:</para>
					<para>
					A TRUE/FALSE value indicating if an SSL connection 
					with the domain is needed to access the variable.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>expiration:</para>
					<para>
					The Unix time that the variable will expire on. 
					Unix time is defined as the number of seconds since 
					00:00:00 GMT on Jan 1, 1970. Omitting the expiration 
					date signals to the browser to store the cookie 
					only in memory; it will be erased when the browser 
					is closed.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>name:</para>
					<para>The name of the variable (in this case Apache).</para>
					<para>
					So the above cookie value of Apache equals 
					64.3.40.151.16018996349247480 and is set to expire on 
					July 27, 2006, for the website domain at http://www.owasp.org.</para>
					<para>
					The website sets the cookie in the user's browser in 
					plaintext in the HTTP stream like this:
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Set-Cookie:</para>
					<para>
					Apache="64.3.40.151.16018996349247480"; path="/"; 
					domain="www.owasp.org"; path_spec; expires="2006-07-27 
					19:39:15Z"; version=0
					</para>
					<para>
					All spec-compliant browsers must be capable of holding at 
					least 4K of cookie data per host or domain. All spec-compliant 
					browsers must be capable of holding at least 20 distinct 
					cookies per host or domain.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</sect3>
	</sect2>
	<sect2>
		<title>Session Tokens</title>
		<para>
		Cookies are fine things to have at your disposal, particularly if you just wish 
		to store things like "the background is green". But for more serious uses, it's 
		vital to be able to tie a user to a session. This is done via the use of session 
		tokens.
		</para>
		<para>
		Simple (but not recommended) session tokens may include a number increasing by 
		one, so that user "hjsimpson" is tied to session id 1, user "msimpson" is tied 
		to session id 2, assuming Homer logged on first and Marge logged on shortly 
		thereafter from the study. This scheme is ridiculously easy to defeat, but 
		unfortunately you will still see it used from time to time.
		</para>
		<para>
		To be safe, a session token should contain enough random characters or digits, 
		must not be predictable and must offer enough entropy (randomness) that it can 
		not be computed for the duration of the session. Session tokens are typically 
		stored in cookies. They also can be stored in static URL's, dynamically rewritten 
		URL's, "hidden" in the HTML of a web page, or some combination of these
		methods. The safest place from na√Øve users (rather than seasoned attackers) is 
		in non-persistent cookies, followed by hidden form fields.
		</para>
		<para>
		As most web application frameworks have matured (read: battle scarred) over 
		the last few years, these sort of session management issues have nearly all 
		but disappeared if you use the pre-canned methods provided by the framework. 
		Unless you have a very special reason and know what you're doing, it's best to 
		leave it to your servlet engine, PHP or ASP.NET to manage your sessions.
		</para>
		<para>
		However, all is not rosy even with decent session management schemes. It's 
		possible to capture session tokens, say for example if they are in the URL of 
		the request (also known as the query string in many application frameworks). 
		Simply using a URL with an embedded session token will make you that user, 
		assuming the session hasn't timed out or the session is not checked against 
		a source IP address, or similar. Also, session tokens which never change for 
		a user could be at risk if the user uses a shared computer. Luckily, there 
		are solutions to these problems.
		</para>
		<sect3>
			<title>Cryptographic Algorithms for Session Tokens</title>
			<para>
			All session tokens (independent of the state mechanisms) should be 
			user unique, non-predictable, and resistant to reverse engineering. 
			A trusted source of randomness should be used to create the token 
			(like a pseudo-random number generator, Yarrow, EGADS, etc.). 
			Additionally, for more security, session tokens should be tied in some 
			way to a specific HTTP client instance to prevent hijacking and 
			replay attacks. Examples of mechanisms for enforcing this restriction 
			may be the use of page tokens which are unique for any generated page 
			and may be tied to session tokens on the server. In general, a session 
			token algorithm should never be based on or use as variables any user 
			personal information (user name, password, home address, etc.)
			</para>
		</sect3>
		<sect3>
			<title>Appropriate Key Space</title>
			<para>
			Even the cryptographically secure algorithms allows an active session 
			token to be easily determined if the keyspace of the token is not 
			sufficiently large. Attackers can essentially "grind" through most 
			possibilities in the token's key space with automated brute force 
			scripts. A token's key space should be sufficiently large enough to 
			prevent these types of brute force attacks, keeping in mind that 
			computation and bandwidth capacity increases will make these numbers 
			insufficient over time.
			</para>
		</sect3>
		<sect3>
			<title>Session Token Entropy</title>
			<para>
			The session token should use the largest character set available to 
			it. If a session token is made up of say 8 characters of 7 bits the 
			effective key length is 56 bits. However if the character set is made 
			up of only integers which can be represented in 4 bits giving a key 
			space of only 32 bits. A good session token should use all the 
			available character set including case sensitivity.
			</para>
		</sect3>
	</sect2>
	<sect2>
		<title>Session Management Schemes</title>
		<para>A good session management scheme should consider the following rules.</para>
		<sect3>
			<title>Session Time-out</title>
			<para>
			Session tokens that do not expire on the HTTP server can allow an 
			attacker unlimited time to guess or brute force a valid authenticated 
			session token. An example is the "Remember Me" option on many retail 
			websites. If a user's cookie file is captured or brute-forced, then 
			an attacker can use these static-session tokens to gain access to 
			that user's web accounts. Additionally, session tokens can be 
			potentially logged and cached in proxy servers that, if broken into 
			by an attacker, may contain similar sorts of information in logs that 
			can be exploited if the particular session has not been expired on the 
			HTTP server.
			</para>
			<para>
			If the user is not at a computer where he is logged in with his name 
			and the operating system is protecting his cookies. However, if he is 
			in say a public library where every user can access the cookies, it is 
			possible that the next user can take over the previous user's identity. 
			It will be very difficult for the first user to convince the bank's 
			card services that he is not guilty of violating credit card security 
			precautions.
			</para>
		</sect3>
		<sect3>
			<title>Regeneration of Session Tokens</title>
			<para>
			To reduce the risk from session hijacking and brute force attacks, 
			the HTTP server can seamlessly expire and regenerate tokens. This 
			shortens the window of opportunity for a replay or brute force attack. 
			Token regeneration should be performed based on number of requests 
			(high value sites) or as a function of time, say every 20 minutes.
			</para>
		</sect3>
		<sect3>
			<title>Session Forging/Brute-Forcing Detection and/or Lockout</title>
			<para>
			Many websites have prohibitions against unrestrained password guessing 
			(e.g., it can temporarily lock the account or stop listening to the 
			IP address), however an attacker can often try hundreds or thousands 
			of session tokens embedded in a legitimate URL or cookie without a 
			single complaint from the web site. Many intrusion-detection systems 
			do not actively look for this type of attack; penetration tests also 
			often overlook this weakness in web e-commerce systems. Designers can 
			use "booby trapped" session tokens that never actually get assigned but 
			will detect if an attacker is trying to brute force a range of tokens. 
			Resulting actions could be:
			</para>
			<itemizedlist mark="opencircle" spacing="compact">
				<listitem>
					<para>
					Go slow or ban the originating IP address (which can 
					be troublesome as more and more ISPs are using 
					transparent caches to reduce their costs. Because of
					this: always check the "proxy_via" header)
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
					Lock out an account if you're aware of it (which may 
					cause a user a potential denial of service).
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			<para>
			Anomaly/misuse detection hooks can also be built in to detect if an 
			authenticated user tries to manipulate their token to gain elevated 
			privileges.
			</para>
			<para>
			There are Apache modules, such as mod_dosevasive and mod_security, 
			which could be used for this kind of protection. Although 
			mod_dosevasive is used to lessen the effect of DoS attacks, it 
			could be rewritten for other purposes as well
			.</para>
		</sect3>
		<sect3>
			<title>Session Re-Authentication</title>
			<para>
			Critical user actions such as money transfer or significant purchase 
			decisions should require the user to re-authenticate or be reissued 
			another session token immediately prior to significant actions. 
			This ensures user authentication (and not entity authentication) 
			when performing sensitive tasks. Developers can also somewhat 
			segment data and user actions to the extent where re-authentication 
			is required upon crossing certain trust boundaries to prevent some 
			types of cross-site scripting attacks that exploit user accounts.
			</para>
		</sect3>
		<sect3>
			<title>Session Token Transmission</title>
			<para>
			If a session token is captured in transit through network 
			interception, a web application account is then trivially prone 
			to a replay or hijacking attack. Typical web encryption technologies 
			include but are not limited to Secure Sockets Layer (SSLv2/v3) and 
			Transport Layer Security (TLS v1) protocols in order to safeguard 
			the state mechanism token.
			</para>
		</sect3>
		<sect3>
			<title>Session Tokens on Logout</title>
			<para>
			With the popularity of Internet Kiosks and shared computing 
			environments on the rise, session tokens take on a new risk. A 
			browser only destroys session cookies when the browser thread is 
			torn down. Most Internet kiosks maintain the same browser thread. 
			It is therefore a good idea to overwrite session cookies when the 
			user logs out of the application.
			</para>
		</sect3>
		<sect3>
			<title>Page Tokens</title>
			<para>
			Page specific tokens or "nonces" may be used in conjunction with 
			session specific tokens to provide a measure of authenticity when 
			dealing with client requests. Used in conjunction with transport 
			layer security mechanisms, page tokens can aide in ensuring that 
			the client on the other end of the session is indeed the same client 
			which requested the last page in a given session. Page tokens are 
			often stored in cookies or query strings and should be completely 
			random. It is possible to avoid sending session token information to 
			the client entirely through the use of page tokens, by creating a 
			mapping between them on the server side, this technique should further 
			increase the difficulty in brute forcing session authentication 
			tokens.
			</para>
		</sect3>
	</sect2>
	<sect2>
		<title>Attacking Sessions</title>
		<para>There are a few possibilities to attack session systems.</para>
		<sect3>
			<title>Session Hijacking</title>
			<para>
			When an attacker intercepts or creates a suitable and valid session 
			token on the server, they can then impersonate another user. Session 
			hijacking can be mitigated partially by providing adequate 
			anti-hijacking controls in your application. The level of these 
			controls should be influenced by the risk to your organization or 
			the client's data; for example an online banking application needs 
			to take more care than a application displaying cinema session times.
			</para>
			<para>
			The easiest type of web application to hijack are those using URL 
			based session tokens, particularly those without expiry. This is 
			particularly dangerous on shared computers, such as Internet cafÈs 
			or public Internet kiosks where is nearly impossible to clear the 
			cache or delete browsing history due to lockdowns. To attack these 
			applications, simply open the browser's history and click on the web 
			application's URL. Voila, you're the previous user.
			</para>
			<sect4>
				<title>Mitigation Techniques</title>
				<itemizedlist mark="opencircle" spacing="compact">
					<listitem>
						<para>
						Provide a method for users to log out of your 
						application. Logging out should clear all session 
						state and remove or invalidate any residual 
						cookies.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
						Set short expiry times on persistent cookies, no 
						more than a day or preferably use non-persistent 
						cookies.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
						Do not store session tokens in the URL or other 
						trivially modified data entry point.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</sect4>
		</sect3>
		<sect3>
			<title>Session Authentication Attacks</title>
			<para>
			One of the most common mistakes is not checking authorization prior 
			to performing a restricted function or accessing data. Just because 
			a user has a session does not authorize them to use all of the 
			application or see all of the data. Imagine a bank web site that 
			allowed you to see anyone else's account?
			</para>
			<para>
			A particularly embarrassing real life example is the Australian 
			Taxation Office's GST web site, where most Australian companies 
			electronically submit their quarterly tax returns. The ATO uses 
			client-side certificates as authentication. Sounds secure, right? 
			However, this particular web site initially had the ABN (a unique 
			number, sort of like a social security number for companies) in the 
			URL. These numbers are not secret and they are not random. A user 
			worked this out, and tried another company's ABN. To his surprise it 
			worked, and he was able to view the other company's details. He then 
			wrote a script to mine the database and mail each company's 
			nominated e-mail address, notifying each company that the ATO had a 
			serious security flaw. More than 17,000 organizations received 
			e-mails.
			</para>
			<sect4>
				<title>Mitigation Techniques</title>
				<itemizedlist mark="opencircle" spacing="compact">
					<listitem>
						<para>
						Always check that the currently logged on user 
						has the authorization to access, update or 
						delete data or access certain functions.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</sect4>
		</sect3>
		<sect3>
			<title>Session Validation Attacks</title>
			<para>
			Just like any data, the session variable must be validated to ensure 
			that is of the right form, contains no unexpected characters, and is 
			in the valid session table.
			</para>
			<para>
			In one penetration test the author conducted, it was possible to use 
			null bytes to truncate session objects and due to coding errors in 
			the session handler, it only compared the length of the shortest string. 
			Therefore, a one character session variable was matched and allowed the 
			tester to break session handling. During another test, the session 
			handling code allowed any characters.
			</para>
			<sect4>
				<title>Mitigation Techniques</title>
				<itemizedlist mark="opencircle" spacing="compact">
					<listitem>
						<para>
						Always check that the currently logged on user 
						has the authorization to access, update or delete 
						data or access certain functions.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</sect4>
		</sect3>
		<sect3>
			<title>Man in the middle attacks</title>
			<para>
			In a man in the middle (MITM) attack, the attacker tries to insert 
			themselves between the server and the client. Acting as the client 
			for the server and acting as a server for the client. So all data 
			sent from the client to the real server is not going directly but 
			though the attacker. It is very difficult for the client and server 
			to detect this attack.
			</para>
			<sect4>
				<title>Mitigation Techniques</title>
				<itemizedlist mark="opencircle" spacing="compact">
					<listitem>
						<para>
						Use SSL, especially for sites with privacy or 
						high value transactions.
						</para>
						<para>
						One of the properties of SSL is that it 
						authenticates the server to the clients, 
						with most browsers objecting to certificates 
						that do not have adequate intermediate trust 
						or if the certificate does not match the DNS 
						address of the server. This is not fully 
						protection, but it will defeat many na√Øve 
						attacks.
						</para>
						<para>
						Sensitive site operations, such as administration, 
						logon, and private data viewing / updating should 
						be protected by SSL in any case.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</sect4>
		</sect3>
		<sect3>
			<title>Brute forcing</title>
			<para>
			There are some e-Commerce sites out there which use consecutive numbers or 
			trivially predictable algorithms for session IDs. On these sites, it is easy 
			to change to another likely session ID and thus become someone else. Usually, 
			all of the functions available to users work, with obvious privacy and fraud 
			issues arising.
			</para>
			<sect4>
				<title>Mitigation Techniques</title>
				<itemizedlist mark="opencircle" spacing="compact">
					<listitem>
						<para>
						Use a cryptographically sound token generation 
						algorithm. Do not create your own algorithm, 
						and seed the algorithm in a safe fashion. Or just 
						use your application framework's inbuilt session 
						management functions.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
						Preferably send the token to the client in a 
						non-persistent cookie or within a hidden form 
						field within the rendered page.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
						Put in "telltale" token values so you can 
						detect brute forcing.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
						Limit the number of unique session tokens you 
						see from the same IP address (ie 20 in the last 
						five minutes).
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
						Periodically regenerate tokens to reduce the 
						window of opportunity for brute forcing.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
						If you are able to detect a brute force attempt, 
						completely clear session state to prevent that 
						session from being used again.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</sect4>
		</sect3>
		<sect3>
			<title>Session token replay</title>
			<para>
			Session replay attacks are simple if the attacker is in a position to 
			record a session. The attacker will record the session between the 
			client and the server and replay the client's part afterwards to 
			successfully attack the server. This attack only works if the 
			authentication mechanism does not use random values to prevent this 
			attack.
			</para>
			<sect4>
				<title>Mitigation Techniques</title>
				<itemizedlist mark="opencircle" spacing="compact">
					<listitem>
						<para>
						Use session token timeouts and token 
						regeneration to reduce the window of 
						opportunity to replay tokens.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
						Use a cryptographically well seeded pseudo 
						random number generator to generate session 
						tokens, or just use your application framework 
						to generate them for you.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
						Use non-persistent cookies to store the 
						session token, or at worst, a hidden field 
						on the form.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para></para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</sect4>
		</sect3>
	</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1>
	<title>Summary</title>
	<para>
	Session management is the fundamental building block of application security. Without 
	decent session management, an application that correctly utilizes all other web 
	application security measures will fall prey to attackers.
	</para>
	<para>When implementing session management:</para>
	<itemizedlist mark="opencircle" spacing="compact">
		<listitem>
			<para>
			Work through the risks to your application and understand if session 
			hijacking, man in the middle attacks, replay attacks, or session 
			manipulation attacks need to be mitigated. If so, use the techniques 
			presented here to do so.
			</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>
			Determine if your chosen application framework satisfies the 
			requirements for safe session handling, and if so, use it. Most 
			do.
			</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>
			Optimize your session handling to reduce the risk from the various 
			attacks, as well as reducing the overall size of session state.
			</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>
			Under no circumstances should you design your own crypto algorithm 
			(unless you are Bruce Schneier) or session handling algorithm. 
			They are incredibly hard to get right and you almost certainly fall 
			to low level attacks.
			</para>
		</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	<para>
	Most of all, don't just believe the documentation. Get out there and test your 
	application for security vulnerabilities. If you don't, someone else will.
	</para>
</sect1>